<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A voice from heaven: or, A testimony against the remainders of Antichrist yet in England: and in particular, the court of tryers for approbation of ministers. / Born by Gualter Postlethwait, pastor to a Church of Christ in Lewes in Sussex.</title>
            <author>Postlethwaite, Walter, d. 1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1498_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208640</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867570</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119886</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119886)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 192:E1498[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A voice from heaven: or, A testimony against the remainders of Antichrist yet in England: and in particular, the court of tryers for approbation of ministers. / Born by Gualter Postlethwait, pastor to a Church of Christ in Lewes in Sussex.</title>
                  <author>Postlethwaite, Walter, d. 1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Livewel Chapman, at the Crown in Popes-head-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill. 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parishes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119886:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119886:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Voice from Heaven:</hi> OR, A TESTIMONY AGAINST The remainders of Antichriſt Yet in ENGLAND: And in particular, the Court of Tryers For Approbation of MINISTERS.</p>
            <p>Born by GUALTER POSTLETHWAIT, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor to a Church of Chriſt in <hi>Lewes</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Livewel Chapman,</hi> at the Crown in Popes-head-alley. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119886:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119886:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Saints and faithful brethren that are in</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland; <hi>eſpecially to that little flock of God over which the holy Ghoſt hath made him over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer;</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Gualter Poſtlethwaite <hi>wiſheth grace, mercy and peace from God our Father, and from the Lord JESUS CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brethren and beloved,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome thoughts have of late (more then formerly, and more ſadly (viſited my heart, that I wiſh may prevaile more upon your hearts. Firſt, <hi>the thought of the greatneſs, the ſoveraignty and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119886:3"/>
               <hi>perfection of God:</hi> the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs of God is wiſer then men, and the weakneſs of God is ſtronger then men. He is <hi>the onely Potentate, the King of kings, and Lord of lords,</hi> and that in the moſt undoubted right, that has made all things of nothing, by the word of his mouth, for himſelf. Vaine man would be wiſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he be borne like the wild aſſes colt; he will provoke God to anger, tranſgreſſe his Laws, change his ordinances, and breake the everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. But who is this that darkens counſel by words with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge? ſhall he that contendeth with the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty inſtruct him? He that repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth God, let him anſwer it. Do we provoke the Lord to anger? are we ſtronger then he? Adde not unto his words, leſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thee, and thou be found a
<pb facs="tcp:119886:3"/>
lyar. The world, yea, <hi>the hight of the people do languiſh,</hi> becauſe the earth is defilled by deniati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the laws, ordinances, and Covenants of God: 'Tis mans deformitie, to walke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own invention in any thing, &amp; will prove his own deſtruction. Can God endure to be preſcribed by creatures? Shall Man coin Laws for Rules of acceptable walking with God in Spiritual, Civil, or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical things? It would be and is horrible impudence for any to do it. All the ſin and miſery in the world, brake in at this door, <hi>viz.</hi> by hearkning to Reaſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> againſt Inſtitution. 'Twas <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s ſin, to do that was <hi>right in their own eyes,</hi> in Civils, <hi>Judg.</hi> 17. 6. much more in Eccleſiaſticals. The Apoſtle held a war with reaſonings and thoughts of men, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4, 5.
<pb facs="tcp:119886:4"/>
Theſe are no competent judges of the doctrine of God in Chriſt, but muſt be overthrown.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>the thought of the fatal miſcarriages of man mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging any thing by his own wiſdom and ſtrength. Eve</hi> became the mother of miſchief to all living, by truſting to carnal Senſe and Reaſon in judging of the tree of knowledge of good and evil. The ſons of God brought the Deluge on the old world, by taking ſuch wives as they choſe. <hi>Iſrael</hi> provoked God to anger with their own Inventions, not onely in point of Worſhip, but in the matters of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, when they follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their own fancies, and the Cuſtoms of men; but in deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining what kinde of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſet up in the Nation; and were convinced of their miſtake by a ſigne from heaven,
<pb facs="tcp:119886:4"/>
God thundering his diſpleaſure againſt them from heaven, and raining tokens of his wrath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: and the tyranny that followed was as teaching of the ſame, God giving them ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of their error as was meet. <hi>Gedeon</hi> would have a new way of remembering the victory by a coſtly Ephod, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> went a whoring after it; which thing became a ſnare to <hi>Gedeon,</hi> and to his houſe. Alas! 't is but a ſhew of wiſdom, that is in Will-worſhip, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 23. and by this means men are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled of their reward, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. and <hi>righteouſneſs exalts a nation, but ſin is a reproach to any people,</hi> Prov. 14. 34. We think by our own inventions to get us glory among the Nations, whilſt we conform our ſelves to the worldly glory of their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but our way were to keep
<pb facs="tcp:119886:5"/>
to Gods ſtatutes and judgments, without adding or diminiſhing; then the Nations would ſay, <hi>Surely this great nation is a wiſe and underſtanding people:</hi> Deut. 4. 6.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>the thought of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Scriptures:</hi> They <hi>are able to make us wiſe unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 2 Tim. 3: 15. to teach us how to behave our ſelves in the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15. how to behave our ſelves in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth: <hi>David</hi> teaches the Church to pray, <hi>Give the King thy judgements, and thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto the Kings Son,</hi> Pſal. 72. 1. The Scriptures are able <hi>to make the man of God perfect, throughly furniſhed to all good works,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 16.</p>
            <p>Therefore, my beloved bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, accept no Law-giver but Jeſus Chriſt, neither in Church nor Commonwealth. Let this be your profeſſion: <hi>The Lord is our</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119886:5"/>
               <hi>Judge, the Lord is our Law-giver, he is our King.</hi> And though <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lords beſides him rule over us,</hi> let us <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him onely make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Name,</hi> that will in due time ſave us from deviliſh government in the Church, when he ſhall give the body of the Beaſt to the burning flame, and caſt the Beaſt and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet into the lake of fire that burns with brimſtone; and from all worldly government in Commonweals, when the Stone cut out of the mountain ſhall ſmite on the toes of the Image: Then not onely the Clay, but the Iron, and the Braſs, and the Silver, &amp; the Gold-government ſhall be broken to pieces, and be carried away like duſt by the wind, and no more place ſhall be found for them; no, not for the goodlieſt Government that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was invented by the wit of
<pb facs="tcp:119886:6"/>
man. And till that time, change of Governments will be the diſeaſe of the world, whilſt Crowns and Diadems are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed from one Man, and from one People to another. I muſt ſay it, although I delight in it (conſidered in it ſelf) as little as others that complain of the great cry of Overturnings, wherewith the world is now Alarm'd. There will be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnings, till he come whoſe right it is. Oh the ſtupidity of men! that apprehend not Gods diſpleaſure againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this world, by the often changes that are made: 'Tis to be feared that this is Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciary, that God may leave <hi>Europe,</hi> and the wiſe Nations thereof, unto themſelves, to walk in their own counſels, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they truſt in, and leave no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their own doings, nor
<pb facs="tcp:119886:6"/>
of their ſtubborn way, whilſt, he paſſes over to <hi>America,</hi> and thence to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> to ſet up the government of Jeſus Chriſt amongſt the Barbarous Nations. The Lords word, brethren, is to me, to you, <hi>Love the Truth, and Peace:</hi> Let us not, of a fond affection to Peace and Eaſe, loſe Truth; yet in our ſtriving for Truth, let us ſtrive lawfully, or elſe we ſhall not be crowned: Wherein I would have every one be wary, not with a carnal, but ſpiritual wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs; walk in your Warfare by a divine Rule, act from a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Spirit, keep to a divine Frame of Spirit, and ſtand eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one in his place, ſtriving for Truth.</p>
            <p>I hope, in what I have done in this following Treatiſe, I have not exceeded. As one of
<pb facs="tcp:119886:7"/>
the Lords Watchmen, I muſt warn men. I hope I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Spirit of God; I am ſure 't is after many prayers and tears; and ſo long I have delayed, till Conſcience made me ſpeak, and the guilt of my delay began to ſtare in my face; and I think I ſpeak not beſide the cauſe: that was the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples fault, that they ſpake beſide the cauſe; and from this, Chriſt argues the carnalneſs of their ſpirit, that would have fire come down from heaven on the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritanes, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 54, 55, 56. Is it not the time of Antichriſts war, whilſt Chriſt is conſuming him with the breath of his mouth? If any, judging of my frame of ſpirit by my phraſe, think me too bitter, let them but take this along with them, That I ſpeak not of perſons, but things, that can't be too ill ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:119886:7"/>
of, when vicious, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Word of God. And for the text I have for what I ſay, if I abuſed it, I ſhall be glad the righteous ſhould ſmite me for it. Read, and judge; and as you ſee cauſe, correct my miſtakes. My time cuts my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to you, ſhorter then I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. I beg this, That as the three thoughts before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed led me into this Treatiſe: ſo prepare to read it by the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them; and I ſhall pray to the Lord to make both profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to you, who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Devoted to the ſervice of your faith and holineſs, <hi>Gualter Poſtlethwaite.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119886:8"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119886:8"/>
            <head>A Voice from Heaven.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Rev. 18. 4.</bibl>
               <q>And I heard another voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſaying, Come out of her, my people; that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Chapter begins with a moſt <hi>ſtately Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> of the certain ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and utter ruine of <hi>Babylon</hi> the Great; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Cauſes of it, verſ. 1, 2, 3. But I ſhall not here inſiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:119886:9"/>
There follows an <hi>Admonition</hi> to God's people, to <hi>come out of her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and this in our text.</p>
            <p>In this there is obſervable,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The means</hi> whereby this War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is given; and that is, <hi>a voice from heaven,</hi> to note God to be the author of it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 25. Here are not the like ſtately circumſtances accompanying this Voice, as accompanied the foregoing Voice. It ſeems this Voice will not be ſo remarkable for any thing, as the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Author of it; the impreſs of whoſe divine excellencie ſtamped on it, ſhall be the onely thing obſervable, challenging our attention to it. As if God meant to ſound forth this Voice, not by ſilver trumpets, but rams horns; not employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the choiceſt parts and gifts, nor men of greateſt power and repute among men, in this work.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Admonition it ſelf;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1. A duty required, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>come out of her.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The argument moving hereunto, drawn from the conſideration of a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble danger, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119886:9"/>
                  <item>1. Of <hi>fellowſhip with her ſins.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Of <hi>ſharing with her in her plagues.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>There remains one thing to be enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into, and that is, who is here meant by the relative Pronoun <hi>[her.]</hi> The antecedent to this relative, muſt needs be <hi>Babylon the great,</hi> verſ. 2. and ſhe is the ſame with that <hi>great Where</hi> in the foregoing Chapter, as appears by the name written in her forehead, verſ. 5. and this is no other, but <hi>Rome Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian,</hi> as appears plainly from the Beaſt that ſhe rides on: neither is this at all controverted among Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>But the great Queſtion will be about the extent of the ſignification of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> or <hi>Rome</hi> here. Surely we are to extend it to ſignifie not onely what lies within the walls of <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is comprehended within the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Par. <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>territories of the Romane juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> And my reaſon is, becauſe the ſame that are called to come out of her, in the text, are by the ſame voice called upon to execute vengeance upon her, verſ. 6. and this work is laid out for the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119886:10"/>
ten horns, or Kings over which ſhe reigns. Chap. 17. 16. And beſides, we know there was the like extent of ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in the Prophets words, from whence the text is taken, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51. 45. <hi>My people, go ye out of the midſt of her;</hi> that is out of all places within the Babylonian Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>But ſtill there remains as great a Queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> How we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of the Romiſh Juriſdiction, and under what notion to conſider the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of it.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that we are to look upon them in their Ecclefiaſtical conſiderations, as they are formed into Antichriſtian Churches. Certainly, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Societies are here meant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are diſtinguiſhed from their ſins; it being made a conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quent of abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in them, to be partakers of their ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. <hi>Come out of her, my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now 't is not like that Civil Societies ſhould be meant: for <hi>Babylon</hi> here, is the ſame with the <hi>great Whore,</hi> Chap. 17. 1. that is out of doubt <hi>Rome</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119886:10"/>
Eccleſiaſtically. For if we take the Beaſt for the Secular State, on which ſhe is ſaid to ride then apparently ſhe is diſtinguiſhed from the Secular State, as the Beaſt ſhe rides on, verſ. 3. And if (with Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> on Chap. 13.) we take that Beaſt to be the Catholike viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we muſt needs take <hi>Rome</hi> Eccleſiaſtically: for <hi>Rome</hi> Civil does not ride on <hi>Rome</hi> Eccleſiaſtical; but <hi>Rome</hi> Eccleſiaſtical rides the Univerſal Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the reference of her Univerſality to <hi>Rome</hi> makes plain; and by vertue of this reference, <hi>Come out of Rome</hi> is as much as to ſay <hi>Come out of all the ſeveral territories of her juriſdiction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus made way unto it, I come to the thing that I intend <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whoſoever would avoid fellowſhip</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>with the ſins of Antichriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, muſt ſee to it that they depart from the fellowſhip of ſuch Churches, and ceaſe to walk in Antichriſtian order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be many examples in Scripture, that ſhew how the people of God have degenerated, through unwarrantable Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119886:11"/>
cohabitation and aſſociation with wicked men and falſe worſhippers: how much more dangerous is Eccleſiaſtical communion, in the times of the Goſpel, unwarrantable to be held with wicked men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 15. eſpecially in ways ſtrange to the Word of God?</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſons of God</hi> loſt their Religion, by marrying the <hi>daughters of men, Gen.</hi> 6. <hi>Iſrael</hi> was defiled with the idolatry of the Egyptians in <hi>Egypt,</hi> Ezek. 23. <hi>They were mingled among the heathen, and learned their works, and ſerved their idols,</hi> Pſal. 106. 35, 36. And in their Captivity, this comes into their minde: <hi>We will be as the heathen, and as the families of the countries, to ſerve wood and ſtone,</hi> Ezek. 20. 32.</p>
            <p>But if Civil communion be ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, how much more dangerous is Eccleſiaſtical communion? The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Moab</hi> called the Iſraelites to their ſacrifices, <hi>and the people did eat, and bowed down unto their gods.</hi> Numb. 25. 2. yea, <hi>Iſrael joyned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto Baal-peor,</hi> verſ. 3.</p>
            <p>Take one place for all: <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 30, 31. the Lord warns the people that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119886:11"/>
they ſhould not imitate the Heathen in their worſhip; not onely that they did not worſhip their gods, but that they did not worſhip their God in that way. And here note, that though the means of Worſhip be onely changed, yet 't is a going to another God. <hi>Take heed</hi> (ſays God) <hi>that thou enquire not after their gods, ſaying, How did theſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſerve their gods?</hi> And that the means of Worſhip is onely minded, is plainly apparent from what follows: <hi>Thou ſhalt not do ſo unto the Lord thy God.</hi> To worſhip God with a ſtrange worſhip, is, to worſhip a ſtrange god: neither will God accept of any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of falſe worſhip, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping in a falſe way, but that a new God is deviſed for the object of it, that <note place="margin">Ameſ. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dul. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. S. 42.</note> is delighted with ſuch worſhip. So long therefore as we worſhip God in the Antichriſtian way, we do interpretatively worſhip the gods of the Antichriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Steven</hi> the Proto-Martyr loſt his life in defence of the Goſpel-way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God, in oppoſition to the Legal worſhip, earneſtly contended for by the Jews, his antagoniſts; amongſt the reſt,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119886:12"/>
for preaching againſt the Temple, and ſo conſequently againſt their National Church, the bond of which was their meeting together at the Temple in one individual worſhip, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 13. For <note place="margin">Cal. <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> although the witneſſes are ſaid to be falſe witneſſes; yet, as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſays, this reproach was not objected to him for nothing; for he taught the abrogation of the Law. But in this they were falſe witneſſes, and ſuborned to lye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wittingly depraved that which was well and piouſly ſpoken.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now explain what I mean by <note place="margin">Explic.</note> 
               <hi>Antichriſtian Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, I mean <hi>Pariſh-Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prove which to be Antichriſtian, I ſhall firſt ſhew what I finde ſtoried of their original.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Potter,</hi> in his interpretation of the number 666. p. 131. quoting <hi>Onuphri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Panvinius de praecipuis urbis Romae Baſilicis,</hi> cut of him writes thus: <q>Whereas originally there was a ſmall uncertain number of Presbyters at <hi>Rome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> they were brought to a certain number and order, by <hi>Cletus</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>variſtus</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119886:12"/>
Popes of <hi>Rome.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> reduced the Presbyters of <hi>Rome</hi> to the number of 25: afterwards, <hi>Evariſtus,</hi> about the yeer of Chriſt 100 appointed and preſcribed a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pariſh to every one of theſe Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters; which Pariſhes were after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards enlarged, and had their bounds and limits more perfectly, and more exactly preſcribed unto them, by Pope <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> about the yeer of Chriſt 260. After which time, <hi>Marcellus</hi> about the yeer of Chriſt 305. limited the number of thoſe Titles, which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently were firſt given to the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by <hi>Evariſtus,</hi> and did by Decree conſtitute that there ſhould be in <hi>Rome</hi> 25, as it were ſo many Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſes, for the more convenient bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of ſuch Gentiles as were daily converted to Chriſtian Religion.</q> Thus he.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Selden,</hi> in his Hiſtory of Tythes, Chap. 6. S. 3. writes thus: <q>For Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Churches, it is plain, that as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane Sees, Patriarchates, (Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archates in the Eaſtern Church) and Biſhopricks, theſe greater dignities,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119886:13"/>
were moſt uſually at firſt ordained and limited according to the diſtinction of Seats of Government, and inferiour Cities that had been aſſigned to the Subſtitutes, or <hi>Vicarii,</hi> of the <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecti-Praetorio,</hi> or Vice-Roys of the Eaſt and Weſt Empire: ſo were Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes appointed and divided to ſeveral Miniſters within the Eccleſiaſtical Rule of theſe Dignities, according to the conveniencies of Country-towns and villages; one, or more or leſs (of ſuch as being but ſmall territories might not by the Canons be Biſhopricks) to a Pariſh; the word <hi>Pariſh</hi> at firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noting a whole Biſhoprick, (which is but as a great Pariſh) and ſignifying no otherwiſe then Dioceſe; but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward being confined to what our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon language reſtrains it. The Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates of theſe Pariſhes were ſuch as the Biſhop appointed under him, to have care of ſouls in them, and were called <hi>Presbyteri-Parochiani,</hi> i. e. Pariſh-Presbyters.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Pariſhes aroſe from the limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Miniſters function. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward there aroſe another kinde of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119886:13"/>
from the limitation of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters maintenance; of which <hi>Selden</hi> in his Hiſtory above-ſaid, Chap. 9. S. 4. thus: <q>Afterward, when devotion grew firmer, and moſt Lay-men, of fair eſtates, deſired the Country-reſidence for ſome Chaplains that might be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready for Chriſtian inſtruction among them, and their families, and adjoyning tenants: Oratories, and Churches, began to be built by them alſo; and being hallowed by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, were endowed with peculiar maintenance from the Founders, for Incumbents that ſhould there onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide: which maintenance, with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſtical profits, that came to the hands of every ſuch Incumbent, (in regard the Lay-founder had, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the territories of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes, tenancies or neighboring poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, made and aſſigned both the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits within the which the holy Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was to be exerciſed, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thoſe that ſhould repair to the Church and offer there; as alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided a ſpecial Salary for the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) was afterward alſo reſtrained
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119886:14"/>
from the common Treaſury of the Dioceſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus you ſee the Pedigree of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes; ſet aſide ſome few that have been made by the ſpecial Orders of Popes or Princes in the dividing or uniting of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes for conveniencies ſake; of which, <hi>Selden,</hi> p. 276.</p>
            <p>Out of what has been ſaid, 't is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that Pariſh-Churches are not plants of our heavenly Fathers planting; and ſo ſhall be plucked up. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 13. They are of mans making, and have ſprung out of his pride, ambition, and uſurpation. They have been bred in the womb of the Apoſtacie of theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times, and brought forth by the working of the myſtery of iniquity. The beſt that can be ſaid of the mother of theſe daughters, is, to call her Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant devotion. They are therefore things that may be ſhaken, and that God hath promiſed to remove, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 26, 27. and therefore it behoves all to flee out of them before they fall on their heads.</p>
            <p>But leſt what hath been ſaid be uſeleſs to the more heedleſs, conſider,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119886:14"/>
Firſt, <hi>that Scripture ſpeaks nothing of Pariſh-Churches,</hi> if we cut out the ſcantling of them by what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged. We have nothing of ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Churches in Scripture, as we have ſpoken of. There is nothing of limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Churches by the Miniſters Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or maintenance by the Edicts of Popes, Biſhops, or Princes of this world: and it is enough againſt a thing belonging to the Worſhip of God, that there is no inſtitution for it, that the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſays nothing of it. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 14.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>that theſe Pariſh-Churches derive their Pedigree from Rome;</hi> There was the copie ſet, after which all the world wrote, wondering after the Beaſt: neither does it help that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their Pedigree from times ſo neer the Apoſtles; for the myſtery of iniquity did work even in <hi>Paul</hi>'s time, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider <hi>what Babels of confuſion and ſuperſtition they be.</hi> Here you ſhall ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial</hi> confounded Saints and Sinners jumbled together, without any kindly ſeparation of the precious from the vile. Civils
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119886:15"/>
and Eccleſiaſticks confounded, whilſt the Civil power of a Magiſtrate bounds a Church, or the priviledge of a Patron by Civil Precincts. Here you may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve great care that all ſhould be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, the walls within which they meet, yea the ground that they tread upon, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the worſhippers; as if God were pleaſed with an holy houſe, and holy ground, without an holy people: which kinde of ſuperſtition <hi>Steven</hi> rebukes in the Jews, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 48, 49, 50.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>When the pretended rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of theſe conſtitutions of men are, the convenient baptizing of converted Gentiles, and taking care of ſouls in the Country:</hi> There lies poiſon hid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe herbs. For the neceſſity of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates aroſe from the exorbitant pride and ambition of the Biſhop, affecting a ſpiritual Dominion, parallel to the Civil Dominion of the Civil Governour. And again, the Curates are the Biſhops crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for the managing of their mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Eccleſiaſtical Dominion; and ſo appointed, as not to infringe the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Biſhop, nor detract from the dignity of the Biſhoprick; and that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119886:15"/>
not onely before, but ſince Lay-founders and Patrons, the Biſhop ſtill reſerving to himſelf, Ordination of Miniſters, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of Churches, and Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of Delinquents: and ſo as the devotion that made men deſire a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to reſide with them in the Country, was ignorant and ſuperſtitious, like the then-Popiſh times; ſo was it ſatisfied with as ſuperſtitious a mean; which therefore layeth no good foundation to the Churchdom of a Pariſh.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>theſe Pariſh-Churches have continued unto our times, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the preſentation of Patrons, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and induction by the Biſhops; who alſo conſecrated the Church, as often as any new one was built.</hi> And here we may minde the known diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Common-Prayer-Book, <hi>viz.</hi> of Miniſters into Biſhops and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates; whereby it plainly appeareth, that our Pariſh Miniſters were reckoned ſtill to ſtand but as Curates to the Biſhop. Now though there hath been ſome change made by the fall of the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; yet there hath not been a kindly Reformation. For the moſt ſtanding
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119886:16"/>
to their old Principles, though their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice be lamed by the fall of the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, wait with hope that the deadly wound that that Image of the Beaſt hath received, may be cured, and he live again; and therefore while the Head labours of the deadly wound, they do what they can to defend the extreme parts. Others, though they would have ſome reformation, yet delight in ſome broken pieces of the ſhattered Image of the Antichriſtian ſtructure, ſetting up their threſhold by Gods, and their poſts by his poſts; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43. 8.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>if we would make a kindly reformation, we muſt not build on An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt's foundation;</hi> but laying aſide all thet is of men, return immediately to Gods inſtitution, and primitive practice, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. 8. As for inſtance: when the National Church of the Jews was to ceaſe, and the floor of Chriſt to be purged; this was the Apoſtolical pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, <hi>viz.</hi> to preach faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto their audients; and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they ſave themſelves from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward generation they lived amongſt, that not onely were unbelieving and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119886:16"/>
in general; but reſiſted the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation that Chriſt had ſet afoot, and with tooth and nail defended their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Law, and Cuſtoms, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 13, 14.</p>
            <p>This done, <hi>thoſe that gladly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their word, walked in the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Church,</hi> Acts 2. And when Antichriſt hath raked the Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church out of her grave, and ſet up Pariſh-Churches, her daughters, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, divided her into Curacies, as ſo many members of her, who cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their Pedigree from Apoſtolical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; I know no reaſon but that in our Reformation we ſhould imitate the Apoſtolical practice. And concerning the Antichriſtian Church-ſtate, 'tis plain that is ſpoken, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 2. <hi>The court that is without, caſt out, and meaſure it not.</hi> That is, ſays <hi>Bullinger,</hi> God will not edifie, but deſtroy it: and thoſe that God acknowledges for Churches during the time of Antichriſt, under the notion of the two Candleſticks, verſ. 4. which in the language of the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are Churches, Chap. 1. 20. theſe are witneſſes againſt, and ſeparatiſts from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119886:17"/>
the Antichriſtian Church-ſtate, as we ſee by the context precedent, verſ. 1, 2, 3. Chriſts Church-ſtate is ſet down in the firſt verſe, Antichriſts in the ſecond; the witneſſes againſt it are impowered, verſ. 3. and ſpecified to be the two Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees, (noting Magiſtracie and Miniſtery) and the two Candleſticks (noting Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches) that ariſe againſt the Antichriſtian Church-ſtate; at leaſt, at the later end of his Raign, ſhall the teſtimony be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, by ſeparating Congregations: I ſay, ſeparating: for 't were abſurd to conclude that they witneſs in word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and comply in practice with the Antichriſtian Church-ſtate, that is to be utterly ſlighted and demoliſhed, like a Caſtle that is to the damage, not the defence of the Commonweal. And how the holy Ghoſt could ſpeak plainer, for ſeparation, not onely from the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Antichriſtian Church, but from the Antichriſtian Church-ſtate it ſelf, (which is alſo a corruption) then in the text, I cannot tell: <hi>Come out of her, my people, that ye be not partaker of her ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119886:17"/>
Thus far for <hi>the riſe, and original nature of Pariſh-Churches:</hi> We come now to conſider them in <hi>their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Does not the character of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Church-ſtate agree very fitly unto them, as you have it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 2? Are they not given unto the Gentiles? Do not men of uncircumciſed hearts and ears, ſtand ſeized of the power of the Keys in thoſe Churches; the major part by far (everywhere, for ought I can obſerve) being ſuch? Finally, does not this preſent party of Gentiles in all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Churches, tread the holy City under foot, and trample upon the ſacred Politie of Jeſus Chriſt? Will they endure the reformation of their Chriſtian Gentiliſm? or the breaking of the Image of the firſt Beaſt, where-ever their Churchdom is acknowledged, and an anſwerable inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the managing of their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affairs allowed them?</p>
            <p>Look on the condition of thoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, where the Miniſter pleaſeth his Pariſhioners, and ye will finde that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified that is written, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 11. <hi>Zions</hi> adverſaries there ſpread out their hands
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119886:18"/>
on all her <hi>pleaſant things. Caſt them out therefore, and meaſure them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Samaritanes pretend the ſame Religion with the Jews, and therefore deſire to be admitted to re-build the Houſe of the Lord with them. But the Jews reject their motion, ſaying, <hi>You have nothing to do with us, to build an houſe unto our God: but we our ſelves together, will build an houſe unto the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> Ezra 4. 1, 2, 3. Let our anſwer be the ſame to all thoſe Chriſtned Gentiles, that would, on pretence of being of the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. yea Church with us, being of the ſame Pariſh: to them that would, I ſay, upon this pretence, equally with us, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſs themſelves in the re-building of our Goſpel-Temple; let our anſwer be the ſame: They are adverſaries; they have for theſe many hundred yeers trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den under foot the holy Citie; and to this their Genius leads them: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no probability that they ſhould further the work but hinder and mar it; eſpecially if we continue our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with them in the Pariſh-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, where they are the greateſt part by far.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119886:18"/>
Saints of late, and heretofore, have expreſſed their ſenſe of what I have ſaid. Mr. <hi>Caryl,</hi> Mr. <hi>Oxenbridge,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sidenham,</hi> in the Epiſtle Dedicatory to Mr. <hi>Lockyer's Little Stone,</hi> thus: <q>The firſt part of his work, that pleads for the holineſs of Church-members, (ſay they) may put you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enquiry whether you <hi>(viz.</hi> thoſe of <hi>Scotland)</hi> have dealt kindly with Chriſt, to obtrude as imperious and ſelfiſh Guardians or Tutors, ſuch a Spouſe upon him, as is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his choice, minde, or liking. The experience of the true and diſcerning Shepherds here, (who are as dear to their brethren, as ſheep to the wolves) doth tell them, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt nine parts of ten, of their flock, are not ſheep, nor fit (ſay they) of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, much leſs (ſay we) of Spiritual priviledges; and then they are rather a Herd or Drove, then a Flock: for few (as the Shepherds themſelvs think, now their driving power ceaſeth) will be willing to be kept by them; nay, many (as they already know) do turn again, and would gladly rend them.</q>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119886:19"/>
And afterwards, thus: <q>If Saints will not (ſay they) but in the company of this multitude walk with God or his people what Goſpel-communion can there be expected? As for the purging of this body, we ſuſpect it to be (as the body) ſuppoſed, and a diverſion from a real duty: for beſides what we apprehend how impoſſible it is, for the far leſſer in number (retaining their preſent conſtitution) that they ſhould regularly caſt out the greater part therefrom; we are informed by our experience, that the worſe and greater part, is more able and willing to a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ejection of the better, then on the contrary: And therefore this ten yeers talk of the lips (about purging) hath tended onely to penury, and the laſt yeers are farther from that work then the former.</q> Thus they.</p>
            <p>I adde a notable Prophecie of <hi>John Hus</hi> that you may read in <hi>Foxes Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrologie,</hi> Vol. 1. pag. 830. <q>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over (ſays he) hereupon note, and mark by the way, that the Church of God cannot be reduced to her former digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or be reformed, before all things
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119886:19"/>
firſt be made new. The truth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is plain by the Temple of <hi>Solomon.</hi> Like as the Clergie and Prieſts, ſo alſo the people and Laity: or elſe unleſs all ſuch as be now addict unto avarice, from the leaſt to the moſt, be firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, as well the People, as the Clergie and Prieſts. Albeit, as my minde now giveth me, I believe rather the firſt, that then ſhall ariſe, a new people, formed after the new man, which is created after God; of the which people, new Clerks and Prieſts ſhall come and be taken, that ſhall hate covetouſneſs, and the glory of this life, haſtning to an heavenly converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: notwithſtanding, all theſe things ſhall come to paſs, and be brought by little and little, in order of times, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed of God for the ſame purpoſe. And this God does, and will do, for his own goodneſs, and the riches of his great longanimity and patience, giving time and ſpace of repentance, to them that have long lien in their ſins, to amend and flee from the face of the Lords fury; whilſt that in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the carnal people and carnal
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119886:20"/>
Prieſts, ſucceſſively and in time ſhall fall away, and be conſumed as with the moth.</q> Thus far <hi>John Hus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither let it ſeem harſh to any that admire the antiquity of Churches in <hi>England,</hi> which they conceive began to be planted by <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> or <hi>Simon Zelotes;</hi> that I preſs the caſting out of the Pariſh-Churches, the deemed ſucceſſors of them. It was a ſaying of <hi>William Rufus</hi> of the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> the pretended ſucceſſor of <hi>Peter; Quod Petri non inhaerent veſtigiis, praemlis inhiantes, non ejus poteſtatem reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, cujus ſanctitatem probantur non imitari.</hi> The like may I ſay of Pariſh-Churches, that 't is conceived were plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by either of thoſe Worthies above mentioned: They retain not their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, whoſe neither conſtitution nor converſation they can be found to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate. And we know that the holy Ghoſt teaches us to ſay of as few as may be, to give a valid teſtimony againſt the Antichriſtians, of two witneſſing Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, witneſſing againſt, and ſeparated from the Church-ſtate, and corruptions of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holy-City-trampling Gentiles: of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119886:20"/>
theſe, I ſay, the holy Ghoſt teaches us to ſay, <hi>Theſe are the two Candleſticks</hi> (i. e. Churches) <hi>ſtanding before the God of the earth,</hi> Rev. 11. 4. whereby the Churchdom of theſe witneſſing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated Churches, is not onely eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and approved, but the much-claimed Churchdom of others rejected, whiles 't is appropriated unto thoſe two witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſeparated Churches, that they ſtand before God; whereby is plainly impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that others ſtand not before God: but ſuch a God as muſt be conceived to delight to be worſhipped in ſuch an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>Thus much for <hi>Pariſh-Churches:</hi> We come now, in the ſecond place, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret <hi>Antichriſtian Churches</hi> by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Churches,</hi> that are the greater territories formed into Dioceſan, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, and Oecumenical Churches, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſeveral Orders of Biſhops; of which <hi>Amefius</hi> thus: <hi>Superſtitio ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Med. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>S.</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>generis eſt in humanis Eccleſiae formis, &amp;c.</hi> That is, A ſuperſtition of the ſecond kinde, is in the humane forms of Churches; of which ſort are Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches viſibly, integrally, and organically
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119886:21"/>
Oecumenical, Provincial, and Dioceſan, brought in by men, as alſo in the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy agreeable thereunto. For Jeſus Chriſt has inſtituted no other viſible, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegral, organical Church, or Church with Officers, for the practiſe of his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, publike, and ſolemn Worſhip, but one particular Congregation, that may meet together ordinarily in the ſame place, to worſhip in all the Ordinances of Gods houſe. Such was the Church at <hi>Hieruſalem: There were added to the Church about three thouſand ſouls,</hi> Acts 2. 41. <hi>The number of the men was about five thouſand,</hi> Chap. 4. 4. Yet <hi>they were all with one accord in Solomons porch,</hi> Chap. 5. 12. <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of men and women</hi> were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, Chap. 5. 14. yet the Apoſtles call them together unto them, Chap. 6. 2, 5. And Chap. 15. 4. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were <hi>received of the Church:</hi> by which (ſays <hi>Calvin)</hi> he underſtandeth <hi>Plebem ipſam &amp; totum corpus,</hi> the whole body of the people, in diſtinction from the Apoſtles and Elders, as appears from the immediately following mention of them: and in verſ. 12. <hi>All the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119886:21"/>
of the Church (that it ſeems were preſent at the diſputation of the Apoſtles and Elders, verſ. 6, 7. and it is very plain they were, by their concurrence with them, immediately upon the concluſion of <hi>James</hi> his Speech, in chuſing bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſubſcribing Letters to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Gentiles, according to the declared ſentence of <hi>James) gave au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Paul and Barnabas, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what miracles God had wrought among the Gentiles by them.</hi> And whereas the Apoſtle ſpeaks of <hi>myriads</hi> of Jews that believe, Chap. 21. 20. it is not to be reſtrained to Jews dwelling at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> ſince it was the time of Pentecoſt, (Chap. 20. 16.) when Jews and Proſelytes came to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> out of all nations: and we have expreſs mention of the Jews that were of <hi>Aſia,</hi> verſ. 27. Neither is it impoſſible for <hi>Myriades</hi> (in the language of <hi>Luke,</hi> at leaſt) to come together, and to hear at once the ſame Preacher. To ſhew which, Mr. <hi>Norton</hi> urges <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 1. However it be, it ſeems that the Church of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> did at this time ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily come together in one place, as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119886:22"/>
required; for verſ. 22. tis ſaid, <hi>The multitude muſt needs come together.</hi> This cannot be meant of the Officers; for beſides that they are the Speakers, it would be incongruous, to call them the multitude: neither can it be meant of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers beſides believers; for this ſpeech of the Elders, is to be ſpeake ſome condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion in <hi>Paul,</hi> to ſome Legal rites, thereby to take off the offence of theſe, that believing, were yet Zealots of the Law, as is plain; and ſo ſuch an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding would not agree to the ſcope of the Elders. Neither doth it ſeeme congruous, that it ſhould be ſaid of any other but the Church of <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> What other multitude ſhould the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Elders expect, that they ſhould come together (unto them, as is impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) much leſs determine their coming together, (as ſome underſtand the ſpeech) about the Apoſtles being come to town? To this agree <hi>Calvin, Beza,</hi> and <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date,</hi> on the place.</p>
            <p>We may adde to this inſtance, that of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. 23. and <hi>Antioch,</hi> Acts 15. 30. But I finde no contrary inſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119886:22"/>
And this I ſay, not onely againſt the <hi>Epiſcopal;</hi> but alſo <hi>Claſſical Churches,</hi> which are put in the room of thoſe Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Churches, by the effectual work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the myſtery of iniquity.</p>
            <p>Theſe are combinations of many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations united by ſubjection to one and the ſame Court of Elders, choſen out of the whole to govern them. Theſe are preſſed ſo far, (at leaſt by ſome) as to take away power of Government, and exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtick Diſcipline from the Congregations, and not onely infringing of it; ſo leaving them but as the Curacies under the Biſhops, and their Miniſters, to have no more power then the Pariſh-Miniſters had, under the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, at leaſt conſidered as the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of ſuch Congregations. See Mr. <hi>Wood,</hi> in his anſwer to Mr. <hi>Lockyer</hi>'s <hi>Little Stone,</hi> Part 2. Sect. 1. S. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I will not (ſays he) queſtion the <hi>an ſit,</hi> or being of the ſubject of this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, whether there be <hi>de jure</hi> and of divine inſtitution, an Elderſhip or Presbytery within a particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; that is, a Colledge of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, belonging to one ſingle Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119886:23"/>
by it ſelf, having power of Government, and exerciſing Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Diſcipline: although I know, men learned, and much exerciſed in the ſtudy of the Queſtions about Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Government, are of the judgement, that there is not ſuch an Elderſhip or Presbytery. And I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, it is right hard to finde in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture either precept or example for it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let us conſider the judgement of theſe Learned men, to which Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to incline; and more too, as appears in his foreſaid Treatiſe, p. 369. where expreſly he gives his judgement. <q>The fixing (ſays he) of ſingle Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions under appropriated Officers, is not neceſſary by any divine inſtitution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Obſerve, firſt, that <hi>they appropriate the power of Government, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Eccleſiaſtick Diſcipline unto the Elderſhip,</hi> That is implied in what has been quoted, and we need not ſearch their Writings, that are of that Way much, to finde it expreſly denied, that Popular concurrence in acts of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is to be proved by the Scriptures.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119886:23"/>
               <hi>Vide</hi> Mr. <hi>Wood,</hi> Part 2 of his aforeſaid Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>This how well it agrees with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 18. let it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. When Chriſt ſays, <hi>Whatſoever [ye] binde on earth,</hi> &amp;c. does not he include the offended brother, to whom he directs his ſpeech, from verſ. 15, and of whom, and whoſe act to the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, he had laſt ſpoken? Eſpecially conſidering that this verſe contains the confirmation of the laſt clauſe of the fore-going verſe, mentioning the ſaid act of the offended brother, to the incorrigible offender, that amounts to the caſting him out of the Congregation of Chriſts Church, and making an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of him: which that we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that it was done, though by him, yet not by him alone, but with the Church; Chriſt, adding the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this act, ſpeaks in the plural num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſays, not, <hi>Whatſoever [thou,]</hi> but <hi>[ye] ſhall binde,</hi> &amp;c. yet withal keeping the ſecond perſon, that the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended brother be not excluded: not ſaying, <hi>Whatſoever [he]</hi> or <hi>[they]</hi> but <hi>[ye] ſhall binde on earth, ſhall be bound</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119886:24"/>
               <hi>in heaven.</hi> And when Chriſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the Keys of the Kingdom of heaven unto <hi>Peter,</hi> his whole diſcourſe lookes on <hi>Peter</hi> as a lively confeſſour of Jeſus Chriſt; his confeſſion being the occaſion of all that Chriſt ſpeakes unto him, and nothing coming in between the beginning and end of his Speech, that may make us thinke, that Chriſt conſidering <hi>Peter</hi> as a confeſſour of him at the firſt, did afterward change his Notion, and look on him otherwiſe. Read <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 16. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they <hi>exclude the ſingle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations conſidered ſeverally, each one by it ſelf, from having an Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip having power to exerciſe Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick diſcipline;</hi> and <hi>ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſeveral ſingle Congregations are excluded from having power of Government, which they ſay reſides wholly in the Elderſhips.</hi> How likely this is, let it be judged. Is it likely that <hi>Go tell the Church,</hi> Matth. 18. 17. ſhould mean, <hi>Go tell the Elders of the combination?</hi> Is it likely that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, ſo tender of the offenders credit, and wary of offending him, by making
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119886:24"/>
his fault publique, that he muſt be told of it firſt alone, then onely before ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay as may be ſufficient to give a Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Teſtimony according to the Law: Is it likely, I ſay, that he ſhould appoint no mean, between the two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and a court of Elders of many combined congregations? But not to ſtay here; it has been proved already, that the Church of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> and <hi>Corinth</hi> were ſingle congregations, that met together ordinarily in one place: And that the Church of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> had her appointed officers, and that the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> exerciſed Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick diſcipline who, can deny? But how unwarrantably ſoever, hard they preſs their Claſſical way againſt the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational; even as hath been ſaid, to the utter taking away of power of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the ſeveral ſingle congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; neither do they ſtay here, but tranſlate the power of Government to their Elderſhips ſubordinate one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other till they come to an <hi>Occumenical aſſembly,</hi> to the officres of the whole Catholick viſible Church of Chriſt, as united in leſſer &amp; greater combinations,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119886:25"/>
even to an occumenical aſſembly. As Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> in the aforeſaid Treatiſe, pag. 371.</p>
            <p>This is altogether ſtrange to Scripture: for if we grant that ſingle congregations with their Elderſhip be excluded from the power of Government, and exerciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eccleſiaſtick diſcipline; yet will it not appear from Scripture that there are any higher Elderſhips, or larger com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binations of Churches then thoſe of the firſt form and of the firſt ſtep from the ſingle congregation; yea the contrary apears, in that the Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> grant them collective, Churches, <hi>(Rev.</hi> 2. and 3 chapters) do ſeverally receive of Chriſt the praiſe of their good, and blame of their evil carriage, each ſingle Church for her ſelf, without any reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on ſuperior combinations; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome of them lay ſituate with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in eight or ten miles of each other; and thoſe that were fartheſt diſtant, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 200 miles each from other (as ſome have computed the Journeys be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.) This is ſtrange, if there were ſuperior Combina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions: and if there ſhould have been, 'tis much that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119886:25"/>
Chriſt ſhould not blame them, after ſo long continuance of Chriſtianity, for not ſetting up his ordinances; eſpecially conſidering the defection of divers of the Churches, to whoſe charge it might well have been laid, as a thing wherein they were acceſſary to their own Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, that they had not ſet all up Gods meanes to preſerve them.</p>
            <p>If it be objected that we read of an higher Elderſhip, exerciſing acts of rule over a Proportional combination of Churches, <hi>viz,</hi> a Synodical aſſembly, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, We read not of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny combination, of any ſuch combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Churches there mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem, Antioch, Syria,</hi> and <hi>Cilicia,</hi> whereby they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Subject unto the rule of one ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Elderſhip, in matters conceived to belong, firſtly to their cognizance, or that may be referred unto them, or in which there may be appeales made unto them; nor when, and how the ſaid combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made and eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, here was no Synod, by which our adverſaries underſtand, an
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119886:26"/>
aſſembly of Officers, reſulting out of many inferiour Presbyteries: I ſay here was no Synod, in this ſenſe. For we read of no forreigners that came to this Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, (if we muſt call it ſo) but theſe that came from <hi>Antioch,</hi> of whom we finde nothing that may import their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence in the decrees of it, but theſe proceeded from the Apoſtles, Elders, and whole Church, that muſt needs mean the Church at <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> and when 'tis ſaid, <hi>With the whole Church,</hi> there is a reflection in the expreſſion, on the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Elders, as related at leaſt in their preſent reſidence and action, (which is all can be ſaid of the Apoſtles, being general officers,) unto that Church onely. So that upon the whole, the reſult is, that the decrees here made, were of the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the officers of it onely.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, here was no appeale from the cenſure of the Church at <hi>Antioch.</hi> For we read not of any Eccleſiaſticall cenſure, that the Church at <hi>Antioch</hi> had paſſed, either concerning the perſons diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, or the things diſputed: but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of diſſention, and diſputation had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119886:26"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> and thoſe that came from <hi>Judea.</hi> Neither were there any refers made from <hi>Antioch</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> as though the matter were too high for their Cognizance, or beyond their abilitie to determine. For the Churches of <hi>Antioch</hi> and <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> were alike, congregational, I ſay, more then Claſſical (in that ſtrict ſenſe wherein the next to Congregational is meant) our adverſaries cannot ſay:) and furniſhed both with extraordinary Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; to which appeals, and refers, in the ſenſe before recited, cannot agree.</p>
            <p>But the reaſon of ſending from <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och</hi> unto <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> ſeemes to me, moſt probably, to be this, <hi>viz.</hi> to take off the ſcandal that came to the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and at leaſt might come to thoſe of <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia</hi> alſo by theſe falſe teachers: by whoſe comming out of <hi>Judea,</hi> it may be alſo, bragging of the Apoſtles and Elders at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> that they taught the ſame doctrine to the brethren there, yea moreover, and it may be urging them to go and ſee if it <note place="margin">Vid. Bez. in. oc.</note> were not ſo; by theſe meanes, I ſay, the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> had (as it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119886:27"/>
at leaſt twice taken ſome offence, and been ſtaggered in their faith, as though <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> had taught otherwiſe then the Apoſtles and Elders at <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> And ſo the errand of theſe Meſſengers, from <hi>Antioch</hi> to <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eruſalem,</hi> was primarily to get ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction that there was the ſame doctrine taught at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> that was at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> for the eſtabliſhing of ſuch as might be ſtaggered, and preventing of farther danger, by the pretences of theſe falſe teachers. And this ſeemes to ſhine forth clearly, in the returne of thoſe at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> in the 23, 24, 25, 26, 27. verſes. Becauſe ſome had gone out from them, that had offended the brethren of <hi>Antioch,</hi> &amp;c. therefore they ſend choſen men of their own company, that might take off the offence, by aſſuring them of the contrary judgement of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to what thoſe falſe teachers taught.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, here was no rule exerciſed over the Churches, to which they of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> wrote the reſult of their conference occaſioned by the Meſſengers from <hi>Antioch;</hi> wherein they throughly weighed the controverted point, to give
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119886:27"/>
a ſound reſolve for the eſtabliſhing of the ſtaggering brethren. There was no rule exerciſed, I ſay; for <hi>Paul</hi> is ſo em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued with the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> by his reſidence there, and deepe hand in carrying on the controverſie with the falſe teachers, that I cannot ſee how with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diminution of his Apoſtolical autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that the decrees of the Apoſtles ſhould be more then materially binding, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe Gods word onely. How <hi>Paul,</hi> that in the defence of this ſame point, cauſes whomſoever ſhould preach otherwiſe then he with the reſt of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 8, 9.</note> had preached: how he, I ſay, ſhould ſubmit unto any Judicature on earth Authoritatively determining of his doctrine whether ſound or not ſo as their decrees ſhould be formally binding, <hi>viz.</hi> as the decrees of ſuch a court, this I cannot conceive.</p>
            <p>And again, 'tis a joynt act, to make theſe Dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ees, a joynt act of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Elders, and brethren; the whole Church concurs to the making and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that under the ſame Notion, verſ. 22, 23. 25 28. <hi>It pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Apoſtles and Elders, with the</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119886:28"/>
               <hi>whole Church. It ſeemed good unto us, being aſſembled with one accord: It ſeemed good unto the holy Ghoſt and to us:</hi> which <hi>us</hi> muſt be interpreted by <hi>Apoſtles, Elders, and brethren,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the inſcription of the letter.</p>
            <p>Now it will not be granted that the brethren did joyne with the Apoſtles in an act of rule over another Church or Churches. Neither will it helpe to ſay, that the concurrence of the Apoſtles and Elders, and of the brethren, was of a different nature. For the text is ſo full as to the involving them together in the ſame act under the ſame expreſſions, even the higheſt, with ſo much punctualneſs, in ſignifying their joynt concurrence, that it will not admit ſuch a plea. Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in the order of their concurrence we ſhall grant, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Apoſtles and Elders did lead the Church in theſe acts: but difference in nature we cannot grant.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that by the whole Church is meant onely the Synodical Church: the reaſon that is given for this, falls to the ground. For 'tis grounded on the Impoſſibility of the meeting of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119886:28"/>
Church of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> together in one place, that hath been refuted from cleare texts of Scripture.</p>
            <p>But be it that we ſhut out the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren from a concurrence of the ſame nature with the Apoſtles and Elders, to the making of theſe decrees, and let our adverſaries make the moſt of verſ. 6. of this chapter, and verſ. 4. of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chapter: will they ſay theſe decrees were Authoritative and formally binding the Churches of <hi>Antioch, Syria, Cili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia?</hi> I trow not, when they have better conſidered of the matter, according to what has been ſaid. Will they ſay that the Elders of a Claſſicall Presbytery at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (for they aſſert no more of the <hi>Presbytery</hi> there: ſee Mr. <hi>Wood</hi> in the aforeſaid tractate, <hi>pag.</hi> 371. and the Meſſengers of <hi>Antioch</hi> are excluded from the deciſion of the controverſie and Decrees here made, by the text it ſelf, ch. 16. 4.) did exerciſe rule over all theſe Churches, ſo far diſtant, that could not therefore be of their combination?</p>
            <p>Neither is it to be conceived but (if claſſes were then in faſhion) they had their claſſical combinations, and <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119886:29"/>
too; and ſhall <hi>Presbyteries</hi> of the ſame order rule over one another?</p>
            <p>It may be it will be ſaid that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Apoſtles, being Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Officers, conſtituted this a Synod. I anſwer, 'tis ſooner ſaid then proved: The text rather repreſents the Apoſtles condeſcending to act with the Church, then elevating the Church to act with them, verſ. 22, 25.</p>
            <p>If againſt what has beene ſaid againſt exerciſe of authority by this meeting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Churches, that (verſ. 28) of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a burden of neceſſary things upon them, be objected; Let it be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whether there be not as much ſaid of the <hi>Aſſertion</hi> of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> verſ. 5. whether therebe not as much ſaid of their <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> verſ. 10.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee how hard it will be to grant any more with Scripture-warrant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if we ſhould grant claſſical El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhips, and combinations: but we ſhall not grant theſe for want of inſtance in Scripture, or any other ſound ground for them. For the moſt Numerous of Churches that we read of, we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhewed at large, that it was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119886:29"/>
               <hi>viz.</hi> the Church at <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> And I conceive that the Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merouſneſs of the Churches we read of in Scripture called ſeverally (even the moſt Numerous, but) by the name of Church in the ſingular Number, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the mention of any more then one company of Elders; I conceive that hath occaſioned the conceit of claſſical Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Elderſhips; but without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from Scripture, as may appeare, I ſay, from that the Holy Ghoſt hath been ſo punctual in ſhewing that the moſt numerous Churches have ſtill met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one place. To the Church of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> we may adde that of <hi>Corinth.</hi> 'Tis plaine that the Apoſtle writes to the body of the congregation, by the epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he gives them in the inſcriptions of both Epiſtles: Theſe he hints their ordinary coming together to joyne in the ſame individual acts when he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes them the caſting out of the ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous perſon: <hi>When ye are gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to deliver ſuch a one to Satan,</hi> 1 Ep. chap. 5. verſ. 4 5. A like hint we have in the ſame Epiſtle. chap. 14. verſ. 23. And here we may take notice, not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119886:30"/>
onely that this Numerous Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> (how Numerous ſoever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be) was congregational: but that this Church had and exerciſed the power of the Keys, for neglect of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which ſhe is blamed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2. although <hi>Paul</hi> had not before this writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to manifeſt his determination: and that the exerciſe of this great piece of the Power of the Keys, <hi>viz.</hi> Power of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication; I ſay, the exerciſe of this Power is put upon the body of the congregation by <hi>Paul,</hi> without any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct application of his ſpeech to the <hi>Presbyterie.</hi> And in the ſame manner that the Power of binding is put upon them, in the ſame manner is the Power of looſing put on them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 6. &amp;c. without any mention of their Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in particular, but wrapping up El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and People together, as which were both to concur, in this exerciſe of <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick</hi> diſcipline, and that with a concurrence of like nature as to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the matter, leaving to each their due place in the body, the one going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the other following in the Lord.</p>
            <p>But to return, if theſe moſt numerous
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119886:30"/>
congregations, were congregational, not Claſſical; I cannot think there were any Claſſical Churches, except there be a Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture produced, as plain for their Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicalneſs, as theſe are that I have quoted, to the congregrationalneſs of theſe that I have inſtanced in. For reaſon will car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry any man to thinke, if the moſt Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Churches were congregationall, that the leſs Numerous were ſo too: and nothing but a plaine Scripture can ſtop the courſe of ſuch a reaſoning.</p>
            <p>And thus the whole fabrick of the Claſſical way falls to the ground, in my Judgement. Their appropriating all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and power of exerciſing <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick</hi> diſcipline to the <hi>Presbyterie;</hi> the ſecluding the <hi>Presbytery</hi> of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular congregation from ſuch authority; together with the whole courſe of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinations of combinations of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Elders, from the Claſſical (that is, the loweſt) to Oecumenical (that is, the higheſt) combination: they can none of them ſhew their genealogie, nor derive their Pedigree from Scripture.</p>
            <p>And <hi>what difference betwixt the Epiſcopal, and Presbyterial Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:119886:31"/>
wherein does their conſtitution dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, except in the exorbitant power of a Chair-man that the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> cut by the height of the reſt of the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> in the ſeveral combinations? <hi>And what difference betwixt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church of the Papiſts and that of of the Presbyterians?</hi> is it more then Circumſtantial? The Papiſts refer the Roote and head of the Univerſality to <hi>Rome;</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> do not: the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> ſubject it unto the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> do not, but unto a general Councel; and ſome <hi>Papiſts</hi> plead for no more, ſave in the interim of the general Councel. <hi>Vide Ellis Vind. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol.</hi> Pag. 16.</p>
            <p>Let it be ſeriouſly conſidered, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is not reckoned the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt from what time he got the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able poſſeſſion of his Univerſal Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, with all the exorbitant Power thereunto belonging; but from what <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Cot. in Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>Pag.</hi> 36.</note> time he aipired to, and carryed it am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly, and had it yeelded uſually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, to ſway Biſhops, and Churches at his pleaſure: and from this time, at leaſt before he proceeded farther, he is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119886:31"/>
reckoned Antichriſt, <hi>and the ſeventh head of the Monſtrous Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 13. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That is no other then the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Viſible <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> has learnedly demonſtrated in an expoſition of his on that 13 of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> lately publiſhed. And this reckoning of the beginning of Antichriſt, is ſuitable to that deſcription of him that is given 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 4. That he <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth and exalteth himſelf.</hi> Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly we may eaſily gather, that the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of a Chair-man, with the fond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of ſome Elders and people, may ſoone turn <hi>Presbyterie</hi> into Epiſcopacy. There needs not an act of State for ſetling ſuch power on a Chairman, and putting Elders &amp; people in ſubjection unto him, to conſtitute either Papacy or Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Thus you <hi>ſee there is little differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence betwixt Presbytery and Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy and an eaſie tranſition from Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery to Epiſcopacy, yea Papacy: and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Perk. Probl. Pag.</hi> 235.</note> 
               <hi>they agree much alſo in nature, being an uſurpation of Authority over the particular Congregations, the viſible Churches of Chriſts inſtitution;</hi> and therefore I have put them together, as alſo
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119886:32"/>
Mr. <hi>Bain</hi>'s Dioceſan tryal, qu. 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 21. Thoſe who ſubject themſelves to a <hi>Presbytery,</hi> ſayes he, as being under it by ſubordination, may in effect as well be ſubject to an Epiſcopal (and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, I ſay) to a Papal conſiſtory.</p>
            <p>Let it be ſeriouſly weighed, that the Apoſtle gives us this Character of the Spirit of Antichriſt, that ſuch a Spirit <hi>confeſſes not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, John</hi> 4. 3. We muſt not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this of a confeſſion of words onely, but it is ſufficient if practice ſpeak it: For Antichriſt acknowledges that Chriſt is come in the fleſh in words, but he denyes it in practiſe, whiles he brings in Judaiſm, or any other way of worſhip that Chriſt hath not inſtituted, into the Churches, according to that uncontrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led expectation of the Woman of <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, John</hi> 4. 25, 26. <hi>When the Meſſias comes, he ſhall tell us all things, viz.</hi> about worſhip, that was the matter in diſcourſe; for that Practiſe contradicts Chriſts being come in the fleſh, when men do not look onely to Chriſts inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in matter of worſhip. And this is the expectation of the <hi>Jewes</hi> even at this
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119886:32"/>
day, that Chriſt will at his coming give in a ſutable platform of his worſhip, ſutable to his being come into the world, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore the practice of Judaiſm muſt needs be a ſtumbling-block. Though men may thinke they differ from <hi>Rome,</hi> they are of the ſame ſpirit, if they walk not according to the Goſpel-inſtitution of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the reaſons of the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>1</label> point, I ſhall anſwer ſome Objections.</p>
            <p>And firſt, 'twill be ſaid, This way of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration that you preſs to be made from the Parochial and Epiſcopal, yea claſſical Churches nulls all (at leaſt the moſt part of) the reformed Churches in the world.</p>
            <p>I anſwer: This tends not to null or <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> make void the faith of the true believers, that ſhall be found in the aforeſaid ways of Church-order: I deny not their faith, whereby they are of the myſtical Church of Chriſt, and accordingly deſtroy not their myſtical Churchdom, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, by a voice from heaven in the text, when ſuch as are in <hi>Babylon</hi> mixt with the Gentiles in the outer Court unmeaſured, and nouriſhed hitherto in the wilderneſs of abominable confuſion,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119886:33"/>
where the great whore ſits Preſident: when, I ſay, ſuch as theſe are called out of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> corruption and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion by the name of Gods people, they are plainly acknowledged to be of the myſtical Church: And yet they are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitely denyed to be of a right order, when they are called and warned to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that muſt needs mean order, ſince their faith is approved; for that being done, there remaines no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be diſapproved but order: for under theſe two, the Apoſtle ſums up all to be approved or diſapproved in the Church, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2. 5. I deny accordingly that the Churches before mentioned, are ſuch viſible Churches as Chriſt hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, and their politie ſuch as he hath appointed; and aſſert, Though their faith be Chriſtian, yet their order is Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I deny them not to be the Woman nouriſhed in the wilderneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 6, 14. But I deny them to be the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks that ſtand before the God of the earth, chap. 11. 4. And this need not be grievous, ſince the Holy Ghoſt hath fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told us of ſuch a diſtinction of Chriſtians. Some are content to walk with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119886:33"/>
in the outer court, with ſo much as will keepe life and ſoule together, and to bite hard in the Wilderneſs, and ſtraggle there, from one greene path to another, ſo they can but get a living. Others God gives power to be his witneſſes againſt the Gentiles, and to ſet up Chriſts owne order in the face, and to the teeth of the Beaſt that aſcends out of the Bottomleſs pit, though they be ſlaine for it, and will not be content to ſerve God as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> will give them leave. Such was the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> time which Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> mentions Gods preſervation of, in his 3 Vol. pag. 921. and thoſe of which Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> makes mention in the way of Congregational Churches clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, pag. 4. Theſe were in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> dayes, and were remembered by ſome amongſt us, but lately dead; they were about an hundred, and they refuſed the common Lyturgie and Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons attending thereunto, and uſed prayer, and preaching, and Sacraments among themſelves, and ſuffered impriſonment for it, and pleaded for their ſeparation before the Lord <hi>Mayor,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Sandes,</hi> and other Commiſſioners, <hi>Jul.</hi> 20. 1576.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119886:34"/>
and in this they behaved themſelves as faithful witneſſes of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis one thing for Churches, to be looked upon as Churches in point of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and another thing for them to be looked upon as Churches in reſpect of outward conſtitution, and viſible order: In the former account, we cannot but give the right hand of Fellowſhip to all that looke to no other way of ſalvation but by the blood of the Lambe: in the latter account, we can give the right hand of fellowſhip onely to thoſe that are after the heavenly patterne, laid down in the Word: we muſt not for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to a right faith, ſwallow a wrong order. Hath not the letting go the right order, let in a wrong faith? Does not the great beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13, <hi>Blaſpheme God and his Tabernacle, and them that dwell in heaven?</hi> meaning the Catholick Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> on the place ſhews at large.</p>
            <p>Secondly, 'twill be ſaid, this laies a ground to queſtion all the ordinances <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> that have beene adminiſtred in any other way then that you preſs for, whether they are to be accounted null and void.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119886:34"/>
To this I anſwer, there is a double de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> of corruption that ordinances have met withal. Some have beene corrupted in the eſſentials of them; as for inſtance, the Lords ſupper in the Popiſh Churches was eſſentially corrupted; The ſigns were turned into the thing ſignified, one Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment denied to the people, &amp;c. When ordinances are thus eſſentially corrupted, they become no ordinances, &amp; are of no efficacy to do good unto the ſouls of men. Other ordinances are circumſtantially corrupted onely, as Baptiſme; although much were added unto it, as anointing, croſſing, &amp;c. yet the eſſentials were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, whil'ſt it always was adminiſtred by waſhing, ſprinkling or dipping in water, in the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. Now when ordinances are but circumſtantially corrupted, we have cauſe to be humbled that we have not ſought God in due order, as <hi>David</hi> for bringing up the Ark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in a Cart, that ſhould have beene borne on the Prieſts ſhoulders: but we cannot reject the ordinance, no more then the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> could reject the Ark, becauſe it was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the cart of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119886:35"/>
When 'tis promiſed that the woman ſhall be nouriſhed in the wilderneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 6. it muſt needs imply that there ſhall be ſome ordinances preſerved from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in their eſſentials, and that Gods, people ſhall be accepted in the uſe of them, and have benefit by them: yet that is no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt coming out of the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (expreſſing (as is plain) the condition of the Chriſtian world, during the reigne of Antichriſt) when they have light and might todo it; neither can it be more an argument againſt ſeparation from the Images of the Beaſt or reliques of them, then it was againſt ſeparation from the beaſt. Will any ſay, that becauſe Baptiſm was valid that was received in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that therefore they ſhould not have ſeparated from her that are called the reformed Churches? Why then ſhould any ſay, that becauſe Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is valid, and other ordinances that have retained their eſſentials, in the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Churches, and claſſical Churches the Images of it, and in the Parochiall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide M. Cotton in</hi> 13 <hi>Rev.</hi>
               </note> Churches, that are but reliques of the Image of the beaſt, that therefore we are not to ſeparate from them?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119886:35"/>
But to ſpeak no longer in general, let us come to that which is mainly drived at in this laſt objection, <hi>viz,</hi> whether this ſeparation do not require rebaptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I am for the negative, as appears by what hath been ſaid; and ſhall adde theſe arguments againſt rebaptization.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>the Scripture ſpeakes nothin of it;</hi> Jeſus Chriſt hath left us no inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for it, who yet was expected to tell us all things, and this expectation own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without the leaſt exception, by our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 4. 25, 26. That of the 19 of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, is all the inſtance that I know, hath at any time been given to prove rebaptization; and this Scripture has been quoted to this purpoſe in the fourth age after Chriſt by the Donatiſts: but in my Judgement <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cent. Magd. cent.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 377.</note> ſo long abuſed. When, ſay they, <hi>Paul</hi> found certain at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that ſaid they were baptized with the baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> he commanded them to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in Chriſt. After the ſame manner do our Anabaptiſts interpret this Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture through miſtake, applying verſ. 5. to <hi>Luke,</hi> as his relation of what <hi>Paul</hi> did; whereas indeed it is to be looked
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119886:36"/>
on as the relation of <hi>Paul</hi> of what <hi>John</hi> did. And ſo is to be joyned unto the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verſe, as one intire Speech of <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſine</hi> diſciples. To prove which, <hi>Beza</hi> argues thus: For, ſays he, <note place="margin">Beza in loc.</note> the particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in all Greeke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies is read with greateſt concent, and neceſſarily anſwers to the particle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, does by no meanes, by no meanes, I ſay, ſuffer that we ſhould breake the ſeries of this ſpeech aſunder, as though the firſt part were to be attributed to <hi>Paul,</hi> and the latter part to <hi>Luke</hi> the writer. And beſides, if there were here a rebaptization of the Diſciples that had been baptized with the Baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> it will be implyed, that Chriſts Baptiſme that he was baptized with, (being baptized of <hi>John)</hi> and the Baptiſme of all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, is not the ſame: that ſounds very harſh. Theſe conſiderations perſwade me to thinke that here was no rebaptizati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and upon this account there was none, becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> upon deliberation findes the eſſentials of a Goſpel-Baptiſm in <hi>John's</hi> Baptiſme. And let it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that any thing elſe was deliberated of by <hi>Paul,</hi> as to the ſolving of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119886:36"/>
whether he ſhould baptize them or no, before he laid his hands on them, after that their Ignorance of the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt brought their Baptiſme into queſtion; and whether the text will afford any thing to ſay upon good ground for the former Baptiſme of theſe, but that they had the eſſentials.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>We muſt either owne our Baptiſme received in the Catholick viſible Church of Rome the mother, or in the Dioceſan or National Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the harlot-daughters and Images of that ſtrumpet; or elſe we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the Churches that ſhall be, and be owned of God, during the</hi> 42 <hi>months of Antichriſt, of which ſee</hi> Rev. 11. 4. <hi>ſhall want utterly the initiatory ſeal of the New Teſtament:</hi> and of this we finde no preſident in Scripture, that a Church ſhould utterly want the initiato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeal of the Covenant of God; neither do I finde any hint that theſe Churches ſhould want it, &amp; be in this caſe unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd, or know of any that pretend to any ſuch thing, that there ſhould be a Church utterly without the initiatory Seal: or elſe there muſt be an extraordinary way of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119886:37"/>
reviving the loſt ordinance of Baptiſme in theſe Churches; and of this I know neither promiſe that we ſhould expect a ſecond Baptiſt, nor experience for theſe hundreds of years, ſince there have been ſuch Churches, that any ſuch have been raiſed up; yet this muſt be received, or the former, that theſe Churches muſt want Baptiſme, if that be null that we have had in the Catholick viſible Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Images of it: for if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it in thoſe falſe Churches null it, every one I think will readily grant that there was not a Baptized perſon left in the world when the Wilderneſs firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſet up particular viſible Churches. For from the Churches reſt till thoſe Waldenſes and Albigenſes, 'tis very rare to finde a man that would acknowledge any other Churches then the beaſt, or his Images, that would acknowledge a particular viſible Church, as Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> obſerves in his expoſition of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cent.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>de Hereſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> chap. 13. pag. 123, &amp; we are indeed minded of an act of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> by his Imperial Edict reducing all to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, to walk in communion with her Holineſs (as his language is)
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119886:37"/>
by the <hi>Centuriatores Magdeburgenſes,</hi> Cent. 4. pag. 315. by which Church that he meanes the Catholick viſible, is plain by the meanes he uſes, <hi>viz.</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering up the meeting-houſes or orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to the Catholick Church; as they that pleaſe may read in the place above cited.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, 'twill be ſaid, But many <note place="margin">Obj. 3.</note> godly men have worſhipped God Zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in this way, and do ſtill; and God has, and is ſtill no Queſtion found of them.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to this, let me propound <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> this to be weighed by every ſerious ſoule, <hi>that this muſt be looked on as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of God unto ſincerity, own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is of himſelf, mingled with much of man.</hi> After that God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his mind, about the place where he would put his name, and <hi>David</hi> had preached it, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22. 1. yet <hi>Solomon</hi> and the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> neglected to build the houſe, the foundation of which was not laid untill the fourth yeare, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. 1. and 37 verſes: and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps this came to paſs through <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> too much intenſneſs on the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own houſe: becauſe this is nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119886:38"/>
before the Lords houſe, chap. 3. 1. immediately before the people are blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſacrificing in the high places, that is done, verſ. 2. neither can I tell how to make the connexion betwixt theſe two verſes, but that <hi>Solomon</hi> was ſo intent on his great match, and providing a Suitable Palace, that in the meane while the building of the Temple was delayed, not being carried on with that ſpeed, that it might have been; and this prolonged the peoples ſacrificing in the high places, that turned unto ſin unto them, and <hi>Solomon</hi> too; and is made an exception in the religion of them both, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3. 2, 3. And yet <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Zeale of God is approved too, and God is found of him, verſ. 4, 5. &amp;c. but for all that, 't is not 1000 burnt-offerings that can make God winke at the neglect of Gods inſtitution. Men thinke becauſe they love God, and are abundant in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that God will not take notice whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they come to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or go to the high places, what Churches they worſhip in: but believe it, they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; and they are as much deceived that think 'tis enough to ſay for a way,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119886:38"/>
that they have found God in it, or rather in ſomething of his that is practiſed in it.</p>
            <p>But there may be good done this <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4</label> way and has been good done in it, errors ſuppreſſed, &amp;c. and thoſe reject it now, made uſe of it once.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, The good that God brings <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> out of evil, is not to be conſtrued into a divine approbation of it, that its name ſhould be changed, and evil called good. Neither is the uſe that has been made by good men of a falſe way of Churches, to be drawn into an argument to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in it. See <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet. Mart com. loc. Claſ.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>ſſ.</hi> 42.</note> common places, pag. 570. I tranſcribe not the Latine (as alſo neither in other quotations) for haſte. <hi>Godly men,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſo long as they were compelled to be in the Papacy, neither could have their meetings otherwhere, if they thought they ſhould any way profit in amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing maners, or any way procuring the glory of God or the Salvation of others, were to ſhew what was neceſſary to the Biſhops and paſtors for that time given, if they could not do it amongſt their owne. But when it pleaſed God to raiſe up Heroick perſons, ſuch</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119886:39"/>
as Luther, and Zuinglius, <hi>which have planted innumerable Churches: leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the graves, and aſhes, and ſmall</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Relictis Buſtis.</note> 
               <hi>footsteps of the Church; it was meet they ſhould betake themſelves thither where they might both live and do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of God, and by this meanes continue among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by ſucceſſion the Apoſtolique faith and life, by joyning themſelves to their predeceſſours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which lived rightly, and ſincerely in the primitive Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſhall we do it without the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>5</label> of the Magiſtrate?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that which is preſſed is but <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> the doing of your own duty in ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from unwarrantable Societies, that the text layes on every particular Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, upon peril of incurring the wrath of God. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51. 45. is a parallel place: <hi>Go ye out of the midſt of her, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver ye every one his own ſoule from the fierce anger of the Lord</hi> burning againſt falſe worſhippers.</p>
            <p>If the Magiſtrate will further refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, 'tis a mercy, ſo that he keepe to his own power, and do not infringe the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119886:39"/>
power of the Church, for theſe two powers muſt not be confounded; which yet few of the objectors attend unto: but the text hath no ſuch proviſoe, as, If the magiſtrate bid, or give you leave, then come out of Babylon. And therefore we are to reſolve with Pet. Martyr, <hi>We muſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Com. loc. Claſſ.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. <hi>S.</hi> 29.</note> 
               <hi>worſhip God holily, and piouſly, though all the Magiſtrates in the world gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay it.</hi> I may adde to this what <hi>Wolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wol. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Can.</hi> 11.</note> ſaith<hi>: If the magiſtrate be an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Church, the reformation of religion cannot be obtained of him; then reformation of religion lyes upon thoſe as their duty, whom God hath furniſhed with neceſſary gifts for it; neither is the conſent of Biſhops to be expected.</hi> And becauſe of this laſt clauſe, I ſhall adde what <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> (a little above the place above quoted in the margine) ſaith:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are ſome which may ſay,</hi> ſaith <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>6</label> he, <hi>Before we depart from the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Magiſtrate in point of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the conſent of the Church is to be expected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They which ſay theſe things, let them <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> conſider that Chriſt hath never ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119886:40"/>
every one is for himſelfe firmly bound to the law of God, whether o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers aſſent or diſſent. If a Maſter have many Servants that he commands to worke in the field, and ſome of them in the Maſters abſence will be idle, ought therefore the reſt to be idle too, becauſe the others do not at all conſent to the common worke? <hi>for this he quotes</hi> Gal. 1. 15. <hi>and adds,</hi> So ought we alſo to do; after God hath made known his truth, we muſt not delay. Conſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is to be expected, if the matter be dubious and obſcure <hi>(viz.</hi> to him to whom it is revealed, as the courſe of his ſpeech makes manifeſt.) Let thoſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>whoſe hearts God hath raiſed up, go up and build his houſe, Ezra</hi> 1. 5. and be <hi>as the he-goats before the flock, Jer.</hi> 50. 8. get we our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, if we can, along with us, but let us not delay our own work and duty, but with <hi>David</hi> make haſte, and not delay to keepe Gods righteous Judgements.</p>
            <p>And ſo much for explication.</p>
            <p>The reaſons of the point are, firſt,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119886:40"/>
becauſe Antichriſt Churches are ſin, The great beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 1, 2. repreſented in ſo monſtrous a ſhape, to ſhew h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ugly he is, in the fight of God, is the Univerſal viſible Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> For it cannot be meant of the Roman Pagan Empire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the crowned hornes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 1. and being in the wilderneſs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 3. Nor the <hi>Roman</hi> Chriſtian Empire; for the Devil gave not the Seat to the Chriſtian Emperours, neither were they admired of all the world, after the healing of the wound, by <hi>Charles</hi> the Great; neither is it a note of perdition to yeeld ſubjection to them; which things are ſaid of this beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 2, 3, 8. Nor Antichriſt, which is the other beaſt, verſ. 11. he is indeed one of the heads but not the beaſt it ſelf; differing in number, original, ſhape, and exerciſe of power: Vide <hi>Cott.</hi> in 13 <hi>Revel.</hi> p. 4. &amp;c. what then can this beaſt be, as he concludes, but the Catholike vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Roman Church? and this beaſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to, and is moſt fitly thought to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the place of the Roman Empire.</p>
            <p>'Tis reckoned alſo amongſt the deteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſins of Antichriſt, that he cauſes an Image to be made to the firſt beaſt. <hi>Rev.</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:119886:41"/>
13. 14. that is to ſet a Church in every Nation, &amp;c. that may have the likeneſs of the Roman Church, <hi>viz.</hi> Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, National, Dioceſan, Cathedral, and Provincial Churches, as Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> ſhews, pag. 233. And indeed, if the firſt beaſt be the Catholick viſible Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> theſe are the living Characters of her, and ſo may well be thought to be the Image; they are as like as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and daughters, and the Pariſhes are but reliques of them. Now theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſins of Antichriſt, the Doctrine can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be doubted of; and thoſe that will meddle with this ſin, it will draw in more ſin upon them, even as the needle drawes in the thred, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 5. Her ſins have reached unto heaven; the holy Ghoſt gives this a reaſon of our text. Take <hi>Beza's</hi> criticiſme, on the word rendred by reaching. He uſes, ſaies he, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whereby is ſignified ſins mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally following one another, and ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one from another, at laſt to grow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch an heape, that they have reached even to heaven. And how naturally Antichriſts blaſphemy of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 6. (that in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119886:41"/>
the language of the Revelations beſt ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the Church) followes on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in his Churches, Let all men judge; and whether that be not the reaſon why the Congregations of Chriſt are ſo evil ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe they are harlots, and will entice, as the harlot, to draw us away to their leud courſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 5. She holds forth her abominations, and filthineſs of her fornication, in a golden cup. <hi>Babylon</hi> hath golden pretences for her abominable idolatries: The preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Schiſms and Hereſies, for a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church viſible; Reverence to the womb that bare us, and the paps that gave us ſuck, for Metropolitane, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, or Dioceſan Churches, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Churches: Decencie, for the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> She hath the alluring ſmell of a Leopard, to draw people after her. 'T is dangerous to come neer her, leſt they be enſnared, being beſotted with her <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cott. in Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</note> ſweet ſmell to the carnal ſenſe. She con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trives all things ſhould be very ſightly, a comely proportion in the number of the Beaſt is contrived; 't is pleaſing to the fancie, and eaſie to remember; 't is 666.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119886:42"/>
She is <hi>Myſtery Babylon,</hi> ſubtil of heart; her ways are ſuch, that thou canſt not know them. Therefore hearken not to her. <hi>A void her, paſs by her, turne from her, and paſs away,</hi> Pro. 4. 15. And ſhe is ſtubborne; if you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to to her, well: but ſhe will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to you. Gods people <hi>would have cured her, but ſhe is not cured,</hi> as 'twas ſaid of old Babylon, <hi>Jer.</hi> 15. 9. I never knew any that would have a through Reformation, that durſt take along their whole pariſh with them to the worke: but have been forced to lay aſide the moſt of them, as the <hi>Jews</hi> the <hi>Samaritanes,</hi> Ezra 4. 1. &amp;c. when they would prepare for diſtinguiſhing Ordinances (as their phraſe is) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing right well, that there were dogs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough (if indifferently all were admitted to the management of that matter,) to ſnatch the bread out of the childrens hands, and drive them from the Table. Why ſhould they be waſhed in the ſame Laver, (at leaſt their children that muſt be waſhed in their right) that may not eat at the ſame Table? Let us take the Prophets counſel; forſake we <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:119886:42"/>
and go every one to his own country: let us waſh our hands of her, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect what God hath determined of her, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Myſt. iniq. pag.</hi> 660.</note> as <hi>Du Pleſſis</hi> once ſaid of the Roman Church. So much for the reaſon of the point. A word or two of application.</p>
            <p>Let all according to their places far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> and facilitate Gods peoples going out of the Antichriſtian Churches, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the exhortation, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62. 20,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be wiſe, Oh ye kings be inſtructed, ye judges, of the earth ſerve the Lord</hi> in this worke; caſt ye up, caſt ye up an high way for the people of God, and take away the ſtumbling-block, and gather out the ſtones out of the way of Gods people.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>take away Pariſhes by an act of State,</hi> viz. the Eccleſiaſticalneſs of them, and all that may repreſent them to be of Eccleſiaſtical conſideration: leave not ſo much as a broken piece of the Image of the beaſt, ſuch are the pariſh, and its Eccleſiaſtical appurtenances, as <hi>Hozekiah</hi> made the brazen ſerpent <hi>Nehuſhtan</hi> a piece of braſs, and brake it to pieces; becauſe the Children of Iſrael unto thoſe dayes did burn intenſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119886:43"/>
unto it, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. 4. So do ye, make them common civil things, and leave no ſhape of the fomer Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſtate in them. Take <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in demoliſhing the Altar of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel,</hi> and the high place there; he brake down and ſtamped to powder the high place. Pariſhes are our high places, in this apoſtacy of the latter times; temples of mans invention. Away with all thoſe conſecrated places for worſhip, thoſe holds of <hi>Mahuzzim,</hi> Daemons, or Saint-Gods, as <hi>Mede</hi> expounds them opening the 39 verſe of the 11 of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoſt. pag.</hi> 104.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel,</hi> as a part of the deſcription of Antichriſt. He renders the text thus: <hi>He ſhall make the holds of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huzzims, with all,</hi> or <hi>joyntly, to the forreigne God.</hi> He paraphraſes thus: <q>And though the Chriſtian God, whom he ſhall profeſs to acknowledge, and worſhip, can indure no compeeres, yet he ſhall conſecrate his temples (Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical holds) joyntly to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian God, and his <hi>Mahuzzims, Deo &amp; Sanctis,</hi> i. e. to God and the Saints.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This may ſeeme a nicety to moſt, that I ſhould inveigh ſo againſt theſe. But
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119886:43"/>
is not God as Jealous as ever? And ſhould not Saints be as zealous? May monuments of Idolatry be better indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then heretofore? Sure I am, the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for the demolition of theſe, is perpetual; and why the precept ſhould not, I know not. <hi>Daniel</hi> 7. 5, 6. and alſo verſes 25. 26. The true reaſon why theſe are ſuffered, is hinted by Mr. <hi>Cotton,</hi> when he ſays, Vial the 7. pag. 14. <q>When the zeale of God lifts up the hearts of people, <hi>Saith he,</hi> then they will not endure a conſecrated place, in all the world where they come. And when this vial is poured out, then the earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of God, and then all the chappels o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eaſe, and Churches of State, and temples of glory, wherewith the world hath been deluded, ſhall be thrown down; they will not leave them a ſtone upon a ſtone that ſhall not be thrown down.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis to our ſhame, that we have no more knowledge of God, then to ſuffer ſuch plain monuments of Idolatry. I confeſs, were it not to cry out againſt the Altar of <hi>Bethel,</hi> and gain an advantage
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119886:44"/>
of ſpeaking to them, that otherwiſe I cannot have, after the example of the Churches meeting in <hi>Solomons</hi> Porch, after the temple was aboliſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 12. I would never more preach or perform any holy duty in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A way with Patrons, or lay-foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> thoſe moſt abominable uſurpers: They uſurpe the prerogative of Chriſt, they will found Churches; not onely build a Synagogue, but appoint the Church and the miniſter; and herein they uſurpe over the Church too. Is it not wiſdomes priviledge to build the houſe, and hew out the 7 Pillars thereof, <hi>Pro.</hi> 9. 1.? is not Chriſt Jeſus the builder of the houſe? and is not this his preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive founded in his Godhead? <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 3, 4. Durſt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſuch tyranny as to impoſe a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter on the people, as theſe do with the helpe of the Biſhop formerly, of the Commiſſioners for tryal of miniſters now? See <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 23. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> on the place, having rendred the text thus: When by ſuffrages they had made them Elders in every Church; He comments thus: The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119886:44"/>
to decree ſomthing by up-lifted hands; by which form of ſpeech, is beſt of all expreſſed the right way of making Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> are ſaid to to Chuſe Elders: Did they do this alone by their own office? but rather, they put it to the ſuffrages of all, &amp;c. Away therefore, I ſay with, theſe abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable uſurpers. And although this uſurpation appeare not ſo clearely in the continuance as in the beginning of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, and though it lie under more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint now then formerly, this will not ſalve the matter: For the Patrons now a dayes hold their right to preſent, by vertue of the firſt uſurpations of their Anceſtours, which yet they alſo imitate and uphold; and ſo now all the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of them: and withall, Scripture will not beare a mincing reformation, Lopping and plaſhing of bad plants: Neither will the blood of Chriſt beare it, and the power of his Spirit. When the fountain is opened for ſin and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, the names of the Idols ſhall be cut off, and be no more remembered, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12. 1, 3. 'Twas evil to ſacrifice and burne incenſe on the high places,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119886:45"/>
though it were unto the Lord onely: God will be ſerved onely in his own way, and wiſdome will ſend forth her maidens, <hi>Pro.</hi> 9. 3. which ſhe cannot be ſaid to do, when men will miniſter to her in a ſtrange way in the doing of it. And mark, theſe maidens are ſuch as go abroad to them that are without, that are ſimple, without underſtanding, and walke with the fooliſh, verſ. 4. 6. let the world, as well as the Church, be ſupplied with miniſters according to Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. That which is ſtuck at much, is the rights and properties of Patrons; the taking away theſe, is looked on as a piece of injuſtice. Remember <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and <hi>Sihon</hi> King of <hi>Heſhbon,</hi> how their hearts were har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by abuſe of righteous principles, urging them againſt Gods commands and his Churches good. Do you ever finde when Images are broken and burnt, groves cut down and burnt, and high places deſtroyed, that there is any regard had unto the right that any had to the materials? The great Proprietarie of all the world calls in theſe rights; who ſhall with-hold them?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:119886:45"/>
I am ſorry for men in theſe dayes, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of the Parlaments diſſolution on</hi> Dec. 12. 1653. <hi>with the Ordin. for impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of publik preachers,</hi> p. 1.</note> that make it a ground to breake up Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, and make Ordinances, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the rights and properties of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons: God calls for them, and they may yeeld them without any dammage; except that they ſhall want a way to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige Miniſters to daube them with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered mortar, and ſow pillowes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their elbows, that they may lie eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their ſins, and go in eaſe to their everlaſting paines.</p>
            <p>A way with Tythes, that old-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-maintenance, that ſeemes to me plainly diſtinguiſhed from the new-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-maintenance, in that argument of the Apoſtle for the maintenance of the miniſters of the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 13, 14. 'tis plain he argues <hi>a ſimili,</hi> from the like; and like is not the ſame. And to this ſuffrages judicious Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> in his Survey of Church-diſcipline: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 1 <hi>pag.</hi> 31.</note> This way of raiſing maintenance, ſaies he, appointed in the Goſpel, is far dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering from that way of the tything in the Law, &amp;c. Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> hath this paſſage touching difference of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maintenance of miniſters, and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119886:46"/>
maintenance. That which was one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required for acknowledgment of the divine dominion under the bondage of the Law, is now turned into the nature of an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or gift for good tidings, but this does not fully teach the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, betwixt law, and Goſpel-mainten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of miniſters, which differs not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the motive and end, but in the very kind. For one is a legal Ceremony, and the other is a Goſpel-inſtitution; the one is Jewiſh, the other is Chriſtian; the one reformed, the other popiſh, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the epithers I find put on the way of tything by Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> calling it the popiſh Jewiſh way of Tything. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Survey, part</hi> 1. <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 29.</note> Concerning the popery of it, I ſhall one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adde what Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> ſpeakes, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the number of the beaſt. The foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, ſayes he, is ſix, that he opens by the ſix books of Decretals: now, ſays he, if you would know why this ſix comes to be multiplied by ten; If you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, all the Government and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the <hi>Roman</hi> State is by tenths, by tythes; all the people muſt give the tenth to the Prieſt, and the Prieſt to the Biſhop, for the maintenance of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119886:46"/>
Church, and ſo the whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment comes to be multiplied, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and eſtabliſhed. All the Roman Catholiques are built upon popiſh Laws and decrees, all which require ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the popiſh Church, and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to that Church, and to the Pope as the head of that Church; receiving do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and worſhip, and diſcipline from that Church; and that was found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſix, in the ſix books of their decrees, and it is multiplied <hi>(viz.</hi> by tenths) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame bookes to maintaine all the Clergy, from the Pope to the loweſt Pariſh-prieſt. But my argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that I would follow, is, that Tythes are Jewiſh; that is much to be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe they are Popiſh: the Papiſts being ſo much addicted to be the Jews Apes; and the rather, becauſe they have ſeemed to make much of the Jewiſh Church-Government, in compoſing theirs; and ſo their Maintenance was moſt ſutable to uphold it. But, which is more, the maintenance by Tythes had reference to the Temple: <hi>They that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in holy things, do live of the things of the Temple,</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 13.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119886:47"/>
that is a ſhrewd hint to their Jewiſhneſs: for they have reference to, and ſo imply a Temple, Prieſt, Sacrifices; which have been revived by the Papiſts, with this maintenance. But yet farther, either Tythes are paid by the light of Nature, or Moral command, or elſe by a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial precept. For as for the Judicial Law, it contains but appendices, explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and functions of the Moral and Ceremonial Law; and ſo I need not mention that in this diſ-junction. And alſo I know none that flie to another mean, to prove that Tythes were not Ceremonial, that may hurt this my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, beſides this of Natural light or Moral command. I aſſume therefore, Tythes are not paid by Natural light, or Moral command. Thoſe inſtances of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> paying Tythes before the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> are not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to evidence ſo much. Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was not of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7. 22. yet was it ſo incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, that it did oblige a man to keep the whole Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 3. Sacrifices alſo are as old as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> Gen. 4. yet part of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119886:47"/>
Law, and aboliſhed by Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 8, 9. 10. But the Aſſumption is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, becauſe no Law appointed in the Goſpel, is inconſiſtent with any Natural or Moral Law of God. But the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 7. urged by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 14. and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 6. will not ſtand with Tythes: Theſe are out of the ſeed of the land, the fruit of the trees, or of the herd of the flock, <hi>Lev.</hi> 27. 30, 31, 32. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. 22, 23. The Goſpel-maintenance is raiſed out of <hi>all good things</hi> that the perſon taught hath. Tythes were paid, the firſt Tenth to the Levites, and they paid the tenth of the tenth to the Prieſt, <hi>Neh.</hi> 10. 38. And thoſe Levites that taught in the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Synagogues, paid to the Prieſts who adminiſtred in <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> the Goſpel-maintenance is to be paid by all that are taught. I conclude therefore, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Hook. Survey, part</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Tythes belong to the Ceremonial Law; which to practiſe, is to dig Chriſt out of his grave, and a character of Antichriſt, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 3. Neither will it avail for any to ſay that they take them not as Tythes: for the <hi>Corinthians</hi> could not be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119886:48"/>
as to their eating things ſacrificed unto Idols, neither in the Idols temple, nor otherwhere, having taken it from the ſhambles; if they eat with the offence of their brother. And if they eat in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols temple, it was not onely evil, for the offence its ſake, but for it ſelf, as in which they committed idolatry, and had fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with devils, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 14 &amp;c. notwithſtanding they made no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Idol, or the things offered to Idols, but went to eat, as to the civil feaſt of their friend, verſ. 19. compared with chap. 8. 1, 2, 3. 4, 5, 6, 7. When we joyn in the ſame action with others, our different opinion will not ſave us from the guilt of it, as the Apoſtle hints, verſ. 20. Theſe Tythes were ſacrificed to Idols, either directly, whilſt in honour of the Saint the Patron with them en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed the Temple that was conſecrated unto him, or her; or interpretatively, by worſhipping God with other wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ſetting up other things (yea contrary things) then what he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in his Church; worſhipping God in a Meſſiah to come, and exchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſtitution, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 6. for Tythes.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119886:48"/>
And theſe are ſtill fixed to the Temples of the Saints, to whom Temples were built in every Pariſh: and though they be not now looked upon ſo much, as Temples of the Saints, yet as Temples of God they are looked upon generally, and the Service thought to be the better, becauſe performed there; and this comes to the ſame paſs, ſince to worſhip God in a falſe maner, is to worſhip a falſe <note place="margin">Obſervant Saints ſee it to their grief, and talk to one another of it.</note> god; for God hath now no material Temple. Neither hath there been any thing done, by way of publike Act, of the Nation, againſt this Superſtition, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by tradition from our Fathers. Upon which I could not meet with the Pariſh, were it not that I come as a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet from <hi>Judah</hi> to <hi>Bethel</hi> to them, to cry out againſt the altar there; or upon the account of the Churches meeting, not theirs primarily. There is a thing like that eating things ſacrificed to idols, that the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> ſtands, as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.</note> a buſh in a my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y hole, to warn us leſt we fall into it. And they that oppoſe it, ſhall it may be fare the worſe for it with the Nations; but Chriſt will give them power over the Nations at laſt. Let us
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119886:49"/>
not deceive our ſelves, God will not be mocked; <hi>All the Churches ſhall know that he ſearches the reins and the heart, and will give to every one,</hi> not <hi>according to</hi> his pretences, but <hi>his workes.</hi> Let us eſteem our knowledge by humiliation, and the love of God, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 1, 2, 3.</note> whereby we ſubmit unto him, and are zealous of his glory, and afraid of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending him; not by the enticing words of mans wiſdome: God will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him that loves him, and ſubmits unto him, though his brethren may hate him, and caſt him out for trembling at <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 5.</note> his word, through which he becomes in their eyes more nice then wiſe: but he ſhall appear to his joy and they ſhall be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>Away, I ſay, with all appurtenances of a Pariſh-Church. Let us not deſire the Silver and Gold of the Idol, leſt we beſnared,, and become an abomination like it, and accurſed like it. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 25, 26. Let us not be confident of our own ſtrength: how eaſie is it for us, or at leaſt our Children, to be reduced to the former Popiſh Church-way, when we have Cathedral and Pariſh-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119886:49"/>
Parſons, Vicars, Curates, Church-wardens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſtill continued? people are apt, upon ſuch occaſions, to be taken with ſuch things, and to ask kow their Fathers, or the Nation hath worſhipped; and this is a ſtep to idolatry, and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 30. that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would not have any of the reliques of the Canaanites idolatry ſurvive them. Oh that God would turn <hi>England</hi> into a <hi>Bochim,</hi> weepers, (as 't is in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin) that we might become weepers for this, That we have not yet aboliſhed the memory of our Fathers ſuperſtition, leſt the Lord leave us to our enemies, to be thorns in our ſides; and to their gods, to be ſnares to our ſouls. See that ſad ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Judg.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. meditate on it ſadly: we have been parallel to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in deliverances, anſwerable to them in neglect of duties; why ſhould not we expect to be like them in the judgments that came on them?</p>
            <p>If to this I ſhould ſay, <hi>Take away Epiſcopal Churches,</hi> you would ſay it were needleſs: but what then means the Cathedral Temples? other things may
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119886:50"/>
be found, 't is like, if you ſearch as God will, <hi>viz.</hi> with candles, every dark hole. But give me leave to ſay, Take heed, take heed, that you ſet not up Epiſcopacie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Saints are afraid what the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for trial of Miniſters will come to at laſt. Some ſpake out their fears at firſt ſight, and wiſhed it came not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Epiſcopacy. Let it be ſeriouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into. I confeſs that at firſt I was pretty well ſatisfied with the Ordinance for their ſitting, ſave that 'tis grounded, in part, on the defence of Patrons rights and properties: but ſince, my ſcruples increaſe. That which moſt ſatisfied me at firſt and made me think favourably of theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, (I mean, as ſuch Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners) was, that their Commiſſion gives them not power to inveſt into Office: but that will not anſwer all my ſcruples now. For though they are not to inveſt into Office, yet they are to take the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of their proceedings from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the Patron, that preſents to Benefice with care of ſouls originally; and I know no qualification that is put on his preſentation, but onely care
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119886:50"/>
taken to preſerve his rights and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and ſo when they do confirm this preſentation, they do in effect inveſt into Office, and ſupply the place of the Biſhop, to give the Complement to the Pariſh-Prieſt.</p>
            <p>And again, is there not the ſame-kinde of Tyranny exerciſed over the elections of the people that was formerly? even as whom the Patron and Biſhop could a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in, he was the man for the place, let the people be never ſo much grieved: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo now, if the Patron and Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners agree, that brings in a Miniſter into a Pariſh in ſpight of their hearts. But 'twill be ſaid, that they are not looked on as Churches. But I anſwer, There can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied, but in many of them there are ſome reliques of a Church, ſome poor Saints that are nouriſhed in this Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that ſhould not be impoſed on. Let it be conſidered what Temple of God that is, that Antichriſt is deſcribed by u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping over it, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 4. was it not the woman in the wilderneſs? <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 6. with 17, 3. Antichriſt raigns over the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal viſible Church, during the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs-ſtate of the Church, that is hid in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119886:51"/>
the confuſions of Antichriſtian order, and lurks among the crowd of Gentiles in the outward Court, that God owns not as a Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 2. and therefore his Remnant is this Temple, during the confuſion of Antichriſt, lurking ſecretly among the Gentiles in their corrupt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, does not the Ordinance for em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powring theſe Commiſſioners provide for the propagation and continuance of our Pariſh-prieſts? for though the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners are not to make them ſo, yet they approve them that are ſo, without any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoſt. pag.</hi> 104.</note> of their ſtanding. <hi>Aaron</hi> would have excuſed his making the golden Calf if he could, when he ſaid, There came out this Calf: but <hi>Aaron</hi> ſhould not have caſt the metal into the fire over ſuch a mould, and then the Gold would not have come forth in ſuch a ſhape: ſo the aforeſaid Ordinance ſhould not caſt Miniſters in the fire of examination over the Pariſh-mould, that is not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and then when any come out of this fire, they ſhall fall into that mould, they become Pariſh-Miniſters, or are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:119886:51"/>
Let things be ſeriouſly weighed; I make not cavils, but ſpeak out of conſcience, and the fear of the Lord. The fear of his Majeſty makes me ſtand upon ſuch things as theſe, whoſe Name ſhould be ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his Kingdome be ſubmitted to, and his will be done in earth as it is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The Lord make his people of quick underſtanding in his fear, not judging by the ſight of the eyes, and the hearing of the ear. Things may have fair faces, and be well ſpoken, that are very foul, filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of the fornications of <hi>Myſtery Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> whoſe abominations are in a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den cup. I cannot but look upon what Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> once ſaid, ſpeaking of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. a late tract of the world to come. pag.</hi> 28.</note> World to come, in opening <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 21. <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>That Chriſt will not ceaſe till he has thrown down every rag, all that droſs and defilement that Antichriſt and Popery brought into the World.</q> I cannot but look on this, as compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending as much in brief as I have ſaid, Jeſus Chriſt will never reſt (ſayes he) till he hath thrown out all the droſs of this world, both of doctrine and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that conformity to the World hath brought in.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:119886:52"/>
I know the great Objection againſt what has been ſaid is, that Miniſters will want their certainty: but for all this, they that truſt in the Lord will ſay, Caſt up, take away the ſtumbling-block, and that with a great deal of fervour, becauſe of the promiſe, <hi>They that truſt in the Lord ſhall poſſeſs the land, and inherit my holy mountain,</hi> Iſa. 57. 13, 14. God hath kept me, I bleſs him, from many a ſnare, by enabling me to take the promiſe for my maintenance; and when I firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the Miniſtery, that <hi>Pſa.</hi> 37. 3. was ſet on my heart; When I was in doubt whether to ſerve the Lord with a little means, or go to ſeek more; yea, rather accept more, for I was offered it in more places then one. And I have been tried whether I would ſtick to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: God hath kept me to it, though with much experience of my frailty: &amp; through this comfort of the promiſe, I have refuſed livings when I might have had them, and laid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down when God call'd for them, in the witneſs of the Truth. That I ſay in the ſtrength of God, is, <hi>Vincat veritas, ruat coelum.</hi> Let us gain Truth with the greateſt damage; for he that is the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119886:52"/>
fountain of truth, is the fountain of good, that hath riches of glory to ſupplie all our wants.</p>
            <p>I proceed now unto a Uſe of exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> to all Gods people to come out of Babylon, according to ſuch Scriptures as theſe, <hi>viz. Iſa.</hi> 52. 11. it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, <note place="margin">Diodate <hi>on the place.</hi>
               </note> ſayes <hi>Diodate,</hi> to the people to come out of earths <hi>Babylon,</hi> and not to be allured and enticed by the unclean and profane benefits thereof; And to all the Church, redeemed by Chriſt, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate it ſelf from the communion and affection of the world, and the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Idolatries thereof, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11. If any ſay, We are in a captive ſtate, yet heare what <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith on <note place="margin">Cal. <hi>in loc.</hi>
               </note> the place; he admoniſhes them, ſays he, that although they be captives, yet that they do nothing for the ſake of their lords, that their condition may be the better, that they ſuffer not themſelves to be drawn away from the pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, that they be not polluted with their rites; that they ſeeme not to worſhip their idolls, &amp;c. aſſent to their religion: The Prophet doth not, ſayeth he, exhort the <hi>Jews,</hi> to be clean,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119886:53"/>
when they ſhall be free, but whiles they ſhall be held captive, and undergo the peril of their lives. Add <hi>Jer.</hi> 50. 8. and 51. 6. and 51. 45, 46. Strive to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in reformation, as the hee-goates delight to go before the flock. Deliver every one his own ſoule; ſtay not for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo as to loſe your ſelves. Theſe are not commands onely, but have the force of a promiſe, that the people of God ſhall come out of <hi>Babylon.</hi> And 'tis as much as to ſay, Ye ſhall come out, if it be not your own fault. And this is a Cordial not to be neglected, as in the <hi>Type,</hi> ſo neither in the <hi>Antitype,</hi> that the Lord gives his people. But what hopes of Deliverance? one rumour comes one yeare, and another yeare comes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other rumour, and in the land is violence, ruler upon ruler, (as ſome render this laſt clauſe.) The Lord endeavours to defend our heart againſt ſuch diſcouragements as theſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. 46. before quoted. Take <note place="margin">Calvin in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Calvins</hi> note on it. I doubt not, ſays he, but the Prophet here bids the <hi>Jews</hi> be of good and cheereful heart; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the earth do often change the Lords thereof: becauſe that mutation
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119886:53"/>
althought it be manifold, cannot at all detract from Gods rule, <hi>viz.</hi> ſwaying all things to the accompliſhing of his promiſe, to his peoples good in their Seaſon.</p>
            <p>My deare brethren, whom I long to ſee upon mount <hi>Zion,</hi> and meet in the <hi>Rendezvous</hi> of the 144000, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Lambe, and ſinging the new ſong: I beſeech you ſuffer the word of exhortation, in theſe following par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, reform not onely ſubſtance, but circumſtance; hate the garment ſpotted by the fleſh. Under the Law a man might not onely be defiled by a leprous man, but by his clothes. <hi>Jude</hi> allude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this type, exhorts us to hate the garment ſpotted by the fleſh, verſ. 23. <note place="margin">Calv. in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Jude</hi> is ſo far from ſuffering evil to be cheriſhed by indulgence, that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to cut off all preparations, and all acceſſaries (as they call them) that they avoid whatſoever is of any affinity or neere to vice. <hi>Willet</hi> on the place <note place="margin">Willet on the place.</note> gives us this exhortation. We that profeſs, ſaies he, the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, are taught that we ſhould not, neither in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119886:54"/>
or in any external uſages, rites or cuſtoms, which may breed offence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our ſelves to the carnal and ſpotted profeſſion of poperie, but to decline in all things the very ſhaddow, ſhew, or leaſt ſuſpition thereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly, take away, not onely Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Notions, but the things. The Lord commands, that the graven Images of the heathen Gods, be burnt with fire, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7. 25. But it might be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, The Silver and the Gold is never the worſe we will therefore ſave that, and call it ſilver and gold; we may put it to a good uſe, ſo we looke upon it as of no holineſs, but common ſilver and gold: Therefore the Lord adds, Thou ſhalt not deſire them, nor take them unto thee, leſt thou be ſnared. <hi>Dod</hi> and <hi>Cleaver</hi> on the Commandments, give this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the place: God, ſay theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend lights, labours with the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that when in the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> they met with Idols covered with gold and ſilver, they ſhould not covet or touch one parcel of the plate, or med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with it: for if they did, it would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare them, and make them remember
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119886:54"/>
the Idol; and from remembring, fall to likeing, and at laſt to worſhip it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is an abomination to God; and he that will keep a piece of gold of the Image, it is the next way to make him a worſhipper of the idol.</p>
            <p>This is that which the Apoſtle means, when he bids us purge our ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit. We muſt not onely purge our ſelves of evil intentions, as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that eat things ſacrificed to Idols in the Idols Temples, that ſaid they went to the civil Feaſt of their Friend, and acknowledged but one God, and one Lord: but as the Apoſtle teaches them, they muſt not eat the things ſacrificed to Idols, nor ſit at meat in their temples; even ſo we muſt lay aſide all ſuperſtitious things and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and have no fellowſhip with wicked men in them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, return not onely to the true object of worſhip; but to the right means that are inſtituted in the word of God. Enquire not how others have worſhipped their Gods, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 30. we ſhould in reformation take no notice how idolatrous ſuperſtitious people have
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119886:55"/>
done before us, but what thing God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, obſerve to do that, <hi>ver.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>This is that ſpoils reformation, that mens eyes do not look right on, and their eye-lids look ſtraight before them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. 25. and ſo as the Serpent beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> by drawing her eyes from inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to carnal conſiderations; ſo are men beguiled from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 3.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Beware of Antichriſt's brokers, and buy nothing of him at ſecond-hand. The Prophet reproved the Hypocrites of his time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who though they would not eat of polluted and unclean fleſh, yet the broath was found in their veſſels. It <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Will et on Jude</hi> 23.</note> hath been the old ſtratagem of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, and his vicar Antichriſt, to deceive men by an image; and men that will not abide Papacy, are yet well a paid with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy; and thoſe thoſe that cannot bear with Epiſcopacy, fall in Presbytery; which how neer of kin to it, ye have ſeen before. As there is the ſtrength and juice of the ſwines fleſh in the broath, though not the outward form; ſo is there the force, and ſtrength, and nature of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy in Presbytery, although it in ſhape
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119886:55"/>
ſhape be ſomewhat different. <q>Therefore <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>vind. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> Mr. <hi>Ellis.</hi> once Popery, ſayes he, rective or in point of Government, I ſhewed was very probable (for the ſubſtance though not the formality of it) to follow upon the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, on the ground that its now endeavoured upon.</q> I do not ſcornfully upbraid any, ('tis far from my heart) but I faithfully warn men of the devils method, whereby he goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to deceive.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude all with that noble Speech of the noble Lord <hi>Du Pleſſis,</hi> 
               <q>May we not <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Myſt. iniq<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p.</hi> 660, 661.</note> lawfully ſay with the Prophet, We would have cured <hi>Babel,</hi> but ſhe would not be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Forſake her, and let us go every one to his own Country, let us now waſh our hands of her, and expect what God has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined of her, eſpecially ſince her judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is come unto heaven; on the contrary, the Lord hath ſet forth our righteouſneſs.</q> And what then do we wait for from the ſame counſel, the ſame propheſie, and therefore from the ſame certainty; but that thoſe Kings and the ſame States who have worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped her, finiſh the work of God, who will put into their hearts to fulfil his will and his pleaſure, to execute his ſentence? and let not the preſent ſtate of things aſtoniſh us in one
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119886:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
day, in one hour, in a moment are his works performed, and this work muſt without doubt be performed. And long ago, as of a thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done, near at hand, and moſt certain, the Angel cried out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; redoubled it, <hi>It is fallen, it is fallen, Babylon.</hi> But God forbid we ſhould forget that other cry that follows, <hi>Go out of her, my people, ye to whom God hath given power to know her, ye which know her but too well, take heed it be not your damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can any man now pretend an excuſe? that ye be not partakers of her ſins, and that ye receive not of her plagues; leſt being defiled by the contagion of her Idolatry and Enchantments, ye be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the ſentence long ago pronounced againſt her, of eternal fire that remaines for her.</p>
            <p>But becauſe we are for the moſt part incredulous and ſtupid; let us pray unto God of his mercy to draw us as a <hi>Lot</hi> out of this ſpiritual <hi>Sodom,</hi> as St. <hi>John</hi> calleth it, to pull us to himſelf by the hand of his Angels, to grant unto us, that we look not back again, and that we may, before he pour down his judgements on <hi>Babylon,</hi> get to that holy Mountain, to that little <hi>Segar</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Zoar.</note> his Church, how ſmall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible ſoever it be in the eyes of the world. <hi>Is it not a little one,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Lot) and my ſoul ſhall live?</hi> Now to him, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, for the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs depths of his Judgements, and of his Graces, be Praiſe and Glory World without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:119886:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
